<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Enchiridion medicum: an enchiridion of the art of physick. Methodically prescribing remedies in such an order, that it may be accounted to the sick-man a sanctuary, and to the studious a library: containing a salubrious remedy for every malady incident to the body of man. Very necessary to be known and understood of all that desire their own health. / Written in Latine, by our learned country-man John Sadler Dr. in Physick: translated, revised, corrected and augmented by R.T.</title>
            <author>Sadler, John, 1615-1674.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 195 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 113 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92968</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S275</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1678_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209145</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868036</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868036</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170251</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92968)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170251)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 210:E1678[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Enchiridion medicum: an enchiridion of the art of physick. Methodically prescribing remedies in such an order, that it may be accounted to the sick-man a sanctuary, and to the studious a library: containing a salubrious remedy for every malady incident to the body of man. Very necessary to be known and understood of all that desire their own health. / Written in Latine, by our learned country-man John Sadler Dr. in Physick: translated, revised, corrected and augmented by R.T.</title>
                  <author>Sadler, John, 1615-1674.</author>
                  <author>Turner, Robert, fl. 1654-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 208 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. for R. Moone at the seven Stars, and Henry Fletcher at the three gilt Cups in Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Robert Turner.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 21".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Diseases --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicine --  Formulae, receipts, prescriptions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170251:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Enchiridion Medicum:</hi> AN ENCHIRIDION Of the Art of PHYSICK.</p>
            <p>Methodically Preſcribing Remedies In ſuch an Order. That it may be accounted To the Sick-man a SANCTUARY, AND To the Studious a LIBRARY: CONTAINING <hi>A Salubrious Remedy for every Malady</hi> incident to the body of Man.</p>
            <p>Very neceſſary to be known and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of all that deſire their own Health.</p>
            <p>Written in Latine, by our learned Country-man JOHN SADLER Dr. in Phyſick: Tranſlated, reviſed, corrected and augmented By <hi>R. T.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> for <hi>R. Moone</hi> at the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Stars, and <hi>Henry Fletcher</hi> at the three gilt Cups in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170251:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170251:2"/>
            <head>To his worthily reſpected friend, Mr. <hi>Chriſtoph. Woodhouſe</hi> of BERKHAMSTEED in the County of <hi>Hertford,</hi> Doctor in Phyſick.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Remember amongſt the <hi>le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genda aurea</hi> of the antient Philoſophers, it is recorded of <hi>Ariſtippus,</hi> Scholar to <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> that <hi>Cum civibus aliquot ſuis navigans naufragio es eje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otus; quum in littore vidiſset figur as Mathematicos in littore depictas: ſalva, inquit, res eſt
<pb facs="tcp:170251:3"/> Amici, hominum veſtigia con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicio. Et ingreſſus civitatem proxima inveſtigavit, qui nam eſſent illic diſciplinarum ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſis, cum his ubi congreſſus eſt ſumma cum humanitate tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runs non ipſum modo, verum &amp; etiam comites illius.</hi> &amp;c. When he was at Sea with ſome of his Country-men, they were by Shipwrack caſt upon the ſhore of a ſtrange country <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome Mathematical figures drawn in the ſands: Be of good comfort friends (quoth he) for I ſee the ſteps of men: aſſuring himſelf and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, that there he ſaw the
<pb facs="tcp:170251:3"/> Emblems of Vertue, and that the Students therein could not be far diſtant; from whom they might expect courteous entertainment: and ſo they found it.</p>
            <p>Sir, I am much encouraged to preſent this little Piece to you, having ſeen your ſteps; and in this tempeſtuous age, wherein there is a Shipwrack of almoſt all delightful ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, the ſteps of men, of lovers of <hi>Minerva,</hi> appearing about your coaſts: I ſay, this comfort affords me ſo much confidence, as to preſume this Tranſlation will be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to you: rejoycing that
<pb facs="tcp:170251:4"/> ſome plants of <hi>Apollo</hi> flouriſh in your pleaſant playns; ſo that I deſire you amongſt the reſt to receive this little branch within your walls; from whence I doubt not but you will gather profitable fruits: which is the Ambition of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours really to ſerve you, Robert Turner.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi> ult. <date>
                     <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1656.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170251:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>CUſtome rather then Neceſſity engages me, becauſe I muſt not be out of the <hi>faſhion,</hi> to put a Preface before this book; in which I ſhall be as brief as may be: for I brooke not Prolixity, nor long-winded <hi>Lectures: ſemel dictum ſapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, ſat eſt.</hi> Then Reader let me only tell you, (if you know not already) that this is a Tranſlation of the <hi>Praxis Medicorum</hi> of Doctor <hi>Sadler,</hi> with the addition of many private Receipts and Experiments of the ableſt Phyſitians now in practice. Indeed I was the rather induced to put this into Engliſh, becauſe it was the language of a City-Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, <hi>that he had rather the book were burnt, then I ſhould ſee it;</hi> which I
<pb facs="tcp:170251:5"/> hearing of, ſoon procured one of them, and now freely communicare in unto all my Country-men; hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it will ſprout like the Camo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile, the better being trod on; and give pleaſant and profitable fruit to all that deſire it; as doth</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Robert Turner.</signed>
               <dateline>Ult. <date>Novemb. 1656.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:170251:5"/>
            <head>The Contents Tabulated Alphabetically.</head>
            <list>
               <head>A</head>
               <item>ASthma Page, 6.</item>
               <item>Antidotes 8. 62, 63.</item>
               <item>Aſtringents 24.</item>
               <item>Abortion 74. 89.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B.</head>
               <item>Boluſſes 9. 10, 11.</item>
               <item>Bladder ulcerated 12.</item>
               <item>Pain in the bladder 56.</item>
               <item>Barrenneſs 77.</item>
               <item>Spitting bloed 117.</item>
               <item>Bladder excoriated 128.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C.</head>
               <item>Cordial-water 3. 4.</item>
               <item>Cholick 11. 25, 58.</item>
               <item>Choler 22. 36, 44 98.</item>
               <item>Collyries 27. 28.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170251:6"/>
               <item> Condites Cordial 32. 33</item>
               <item>Cancers 38.</item>
               <item>Cough 67. 71, 72, 73, 103, 135.</item>
               <item>Catarrh 70. 107, 135.</item>
               <item>Cornes 110.</item>
               <item>Cramp 175. 237.</item>
               <item>Conception 143.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D.</head>
               <item>Cecoctions 34 35.</item>
               <item>Dropſy 46. 47, 49, 70, 92, 116, 121. 131, 132</item>
               <item>Eſy deliverance 57.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E.</head>
               <item>Eyes inflamed 27.</item>
               <item>Watry-Eyes 28.</item>
               <item>Eyes ulcerated 29.</item>
               <item>Eyes dym and itching 29. 30, 31, 32.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E.</head>
               <item>Epilepſy 51.</item>
               <item>Electuaries 51.</item>
               <item>Epithcmes 110.</item>
               <item>Pain in the Eares 125.</item>
               <item>Ecl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gme 132.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:170251:6"/>
               <head>F.</head>
               <item>Flegme 23. 37, 99.</item>
               <item>Feavers 35. 96, 110, 115, 130.</item>
               <item>French-Pox 39. 41, 54.</item>
               <item>Falling-ſickneſs 51. 52, 66.</item>
               <item>Flix 63. 64, 111.</item>
               <item>Feaver-hectick 78.</item>
               <item>Fomentations 101.</item>
               <item>Red Face 103.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G.</head>
               <item>Gout 11. 107, 113, 124.</item>
               <item>Gonorrhea 54. 55.</item>
               <item>Pain in the Guts 59.</item>
               <item>Gargariſmes 106. 107.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H.</head>
               <item>Head-ach 24. 25, 110.</item>
               <item>To comfort the heart 57. 62.</item>
               <item>Hoarſeneſs 69.</item>
               <item>Hicket 74.</item>
               <item>Hemorrhoids 97.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:170251:7"/>
               <head>I.</head>
               <item>Inteſtines 26.</item>
               <item>Infection 34.</item>
               <item>Tellow Iaundiſe 97. 110.</item>
               <item>Inceſſions 112.</item>
               <item>Juleps 114.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>K.</head>
               <item>Lungs Corrupted 10. 75.</item>
               <item>Liver inflamed 49. 73, 97, 126.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L.</head>
               <item>Looſeneſs 58. 63, 64.</item>
               <item>Liver obſtructed 64.</item>
               <item>Liniments 121.</item>
               <item>To ſtir up luſt 123.</item>
               <item>Loho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h 134.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M.</head>
               <item>Melancholy 23. 38, 43, 45, 46, 119, 120.</item>
               <item>Suffocations of the matrix 52.</item>
               <item>Minde-diſtempers 182.</item>
               <item>Matrix coming down 88. 100.</item>
               <item>Palate of the Mouth 111</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170251:7"/>
               <item> Milks 128. 129.</item>
               <item>Maſticatories 237.</item>
               <item>A Peſſary for the Molo 143.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O.</head>
               <item>Obſtructious 42. 43 49.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P.</head>
               <item>Phyſick 4. 5.</item>
               <item>Pleuriſy 21. 22, 36, 37 99, 103, 117, 118, 119, 135.</item>
               <item>Plague 61. 62, 63.</item>
               <item>Palſey 67. 122.</item>
               <item>Plaiſters 99.</item>
               <item>Small-Pox 109.</item>
               <item>Peſſaries 239.</item>
               <item>Pills 142.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Q.</head>
               <item>Quinſy 84. 107. 108.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R.</head>
               <item>Reynes ulcerated 12. 56, 80.</item>
               <item>Reynes inflamed 14. 18, 19, 51, 54, 55, 102.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170251:8"/>
               <item> Rupture 20. 78.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S.</head>
               <item>Stone 1. 2, 3, 12, 55 60 112.</item>
               <item>Stomach 7. 14 15, 16<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 71.</item>
               <item>Splcen 17. 45. 97, 82.</item>
               <item>Weak ſight 67. 68.</item>
               <item>Sleep to procure 81. 101. 122.</item>
               <item>Swooning 93.</item>
               <item>Scabs 103.</item>
               <item>Scurvy 105.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T.</head>
               <item>Tearmes to bring down 7. 65, 126, 238. 239.</item>
               <item>Tumors 20.</item>
               <item>Tympany 25.</item>
               <item>To ſtop the Tearmes 66. 175.</item>
               <item>Tooth-ach</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>V.</head>
               <item>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>entricles to ſtrengthen 5.</item>
               <item>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine to cool 13. 53, 129.</item>
               <item>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers 12. 13.</item>
               <item>Vomiting 15. 16, 103.</item>
               <item>Venereal pain 8. 39.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170251:8"/>
               <item> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine to provoke 48.</item>
               <item>To provoke venery 65.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>W.</head>
               <item>Womb ſwelled 18.</item>
               <item>Watriſh humors 40. 76.</item>
               <item>Winde 60. 61<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 97.</item>
               <item>Such as cannot hold their water 60. 61, 80.</item>
               <item>Wormes 103, 127.</item>
               <item>Whites 106. 107, 108.</item>
               <item>Womb ſwelled 102.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:170251:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170251:9"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Sick Mans Sanctuary:</hi> Or, the <hi>Studious Mans Library:</hi> Wherein The Remedy of every Malady is ranged into an Alphabeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Order.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 1. <hi>Aquae;</hi> or, Waters.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Water for the Stone.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake of Straw-berryes one pound and a half, Spirit of Wine two pound, Juyce of Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons three ounces; mingle them, and let them be infuſed for the ſpace of twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty dayes; afterwards put up in conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170251:10"/> glaſſes: and the doſe of it is one ounce.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another Water for the Stone.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Water of Camomile, the Water of Pellitory; Ivy with the Berryes, Horſe-Radiſh root, Parſly, the Water of Fennel with the roots, of Broom Flowers, Thime, of each one pound and a half; white-Wine four pound, Venice Turpentine two pound, the Seeds of Annis, and Caraway, of each half a pound; Grummel Seed three ounces, Cinamon one ounce and half, the Roots of Sperage two ounces; Let ſuch be pulverized, as are to be: Mingle them, and diſtil them according to art: the doſe is two ounces and a half, with white-Wine and Sugar; of each one ounce.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Water to diſperſe the Stone.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Water of Parſly, Straw-berries, the beſt Wine, of each two pound; tart Maligo one pound: firſt mingle both the waters, and then the Wine, with one pound of white Sugar,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170251:10"/> continually ſtirring of it; expoſing it to the Sun for the ſpace of eight dayes: the doſe is three ſpoonfulls morning and night before Supper.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another Water againſt the Stone.</head>
                  <p>Take the four quarters of a hare, white-Wine four pound, the Flowers of Camomile and Broom, of each one p. and a half, Juniper berries, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Seeds of ſtone-Crop, Parſly, Grummel and Annis, of each one ounce; pure Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine three ounces, Nutmeg half an ounce; diſtil them together: the doſe is three ounc. upon an empty ſtomack; and after it is taken, walk three hours.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Cordial and heart-chearing Water.</head>
                  <p>Take the VVaters of Borage, Bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſs, and Roſemary, of each half a pound; Roſe-water three pound, Mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go-Sack two pound, Cinamon 3 ounces and half; Nutmegs three ounc. of all the Sanders of each half an ounce; Mace, Citron Pill, Cloves, Ivory ſhavings,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170251:11"/> ſweet Cane, Setwel, the Roots of Enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacampane, Angelico, of each half an ounce; Galangal three dragmes: Let theſe be diſtilled according to art; the doſe of the VVater is two ounces, with one dragme of <hi>Manus Chriſti</hi> diſſolved therein.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another Cordial VVater.</head>
                  <p>Take of Cloves, Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>langa, <note place="margin">Aq. <hi>Mirabilis Coll. Phyſic.</hi> London.</note> Cubebs, Mace, Cardamoms, Nutmegs, Ginger, of each one dragme; Juyce of Selendine half a pound, Spirit of Wine one pound, white-VVine three pound: infuſe them twenty four hours, and draw off two pound with an Alembeck: the doſe is three ſpoonfulls.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Water againſt the Pthyſick.</head>
                  <p>Take of Pine Kernels, the Pulpe of a Capon, of each four ounces; Plantain half a pound; St Johns-wort, Betony, Violets, Sage, Dittany, the greater Comfrey, of each three ounces; Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Nutmegs, of each three dragmes; Liverwort, Lungwort, of each 1 ounce;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170251:11"/> Aſſes milk, as much as will ſuffice: make thereof an infuſion, afterwards let it be diſtilled; and the doſe thereof is two ounces.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take a Capon the Guts <note place="margin">Aq. <hi>Caponis Coll. Phyſic.</hi> London.</note> being pulled out, cut in ſmall pieces, the fat being taken away, boyled in a ſufficient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Spring-water, in a cloſe Veſſel; take of this broth 3 pound, Borage and Violet-water, of each one pound and a half, white Wine one pound, red Roſe-Leaves two dragmes and an half; the Flowers of Borage, Violets, and Bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſs, of each one dragme; pieces of Bread hot out of the oven half a pound, Cinamon bruiſed half an ounce: ſtill it in a glaſſe Still according to art: the doſe of this Water is three ounces mornings and night.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Water to corroburate the Ventricle.</head>
                  <p>Take Mace, Cloves, Galanga, ſweet Cane, Mint, Worm-wood, Maiden-hair, Rhabarbe; Ginger condited:
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170251:12"/> Maſtick, of each ſix dragmes; Hot wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Mint-water, Maligo Wine, of each one pinte: Let the ingredients be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed in the liquors, and afterwards di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill them: the doſe is one ounce, when the Stomack is faint.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Water for the Aſthma.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Decoction of French Barly five pin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, Liquoriſh bruiſed, Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins of the Sun ſtoned, of each ſix ounc. Figgs 30<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> blanched Almonds five ounces, Orris root two ounces and an half, Dates 12. Maiden-hair, Hyſſop, Hore-hound, Peny-royal, of each one handful; the roots of Enulacampane, Foxes Lungs, of each two ounces; Gum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hraganth, Fenugreek, of each one ounce; the Flowers of Bugloſs, Borage, of each two Pugills; the Seeds of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, Fennel, and Caraway, of each half an ounce; Hony of Roſes 12 ounces, the four greater Cool Seeds, of each half an ounce; Saffron two dragmes: Let all theſe be ſliced, pulverized, and infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>illed according <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>art upon a gentle firo who doſe thereof is two ounces every third hour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:170251:12"/>
                  <head>A noble and moſt excellent Water, to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roborate a cold Stomach.</head>
                  <p>Take of Aqua vitae three pintes, long and black Pepper, of each two ounces; both the Cardamoms, of each half an ounce; Ginger one ounce, Cinamon, Mace, Nutmeg, of each one ounce and half; Aniſeed three ounces, Galanga, ſweet Cane, Cloves, of each half an ounce: let them be reduced into a powder, and infuſed for a whole night, and in the next morning add Claret-Wine ſeven pints, and ſo diſtil it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to art: the doſe hereof is two ounces in a morning faſting.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Water to bring down the Tearms.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Waters of Peni-royal, and Mugwort, of each four pints, Hyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſop, Hore-hound, Marjoran, Betony, Thime, Balm, of each one handful; the Leaves of Bayes, and Aſh, of each one Pugil; Saffron one dragme, Caſſia-wood two dragmes, Myrrhe one ounce, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ian one dragme, Madder-roots three ounces, Orris half an ounce, Savine one
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170251:13"/> ounce, the Seeds of Annis and Fennel, of each three dragms; Caſtoreum half an ounce: let them be infuſed in the aforeſaid liquor, and diſtilled according to art: the doſe is three ounces with a little Sugar.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Doctor Sadlers Treacle, or Epidemical Antidote.</head>
                  <p>Take of Carret-ſeed two ſcruples; the Seeds of Annis, Fennel, Madder, Galbanum, Staechados, all the three Sanders, Storax, Camphire, of each two dragmes; Parſly-ſeed, red Roſes, Peni-royal, Rue, Borage Flowers, of each one dragm, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſtoreum two ſcrup. Opium two dragms, Hore-hound one dragme and half, Bdellium, Opoponax, Aloes, Cloves, Mace, Galanga, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, Bole-Armoniack, Tormentil, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelico, Ginger, Setwel, of each two dragms; Troches of Vipers half an ounc. Sagapenum one dragm, Cardamoms, Roſemary, Spikenard, Scordium, Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood; the leſſer Centory, Mint, Hyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſop, of each half a dragme; Gentian, Bay-berryes, Myrrhe, Birth-wort, Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, ſweet Cane, Olibanum, Saffron,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170251:13"/> of each half an ounce; Acaſia one ounc. Aloes, Agarick, Orris, of each one dragme; Dittany two dragms and half; the three Peppers, of each half a ſcrup. the Seeds of Piony with the Roots, of each one ſcruple; Venice-Turpentine three ounces, Liquoriſh one ounce, Rhabarbe ſix dragmes, Agarick three dragms, Caſſia newly extracted 3 ounc. clarified Honey four pound and half, Rheniſh-Wine one pinte and half: diſſolve the Gums in the Wine, and the reſt finely pulverized, mingle them all together in an earthen Veſſel, fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it upon hot Embers, the Veſſel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cloſe covered.</p>
                  <p>Half a dragme of this taken in two ounces of the Decoction of Betony or Roſemary, after the firſt ſleep, doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly allay the vehement pains of the Head.</p>
                  <p>One dragme of it taken in Mugwort-water, doth bring down the Tearms.</p>
                  <p>It helpeth ſuch as are troubled with Epileptick fits, by taking one dragme of it, in Pyony water.</p>
                  <p>It reſiſts poyſon, and obſtructs it's maligne influence from invading the Vitals. If one dragme of it be taken in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170251:14"/> a draught of Carduus water.</p>
                  <p>It is good againſt the Collick-paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: if one dragme of it be diſſolved in white-Wine, where Camomile was boyled, it cureth the Dropſy, if the droptical do take two ſcruples and a half in <hi>Aqua Ebuli.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is alſo good againſt all the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Lungs, if two ſcruples be taken for a doſe, either in Maiden-hair water, or broth, upon an empty Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Boli;</hi> or, Boluſſes.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Bolus againſt the corruption of the Lungs.</head>
                  <p>TAke of the ſpecies of <note place="margin">London <hi>Diſpenſat.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Hiera picra</hi> two ſcruples, Flower of Brimſtone one ſcruple, Turpentine waſhed ſix dragmes: mingle them upon a ſtone, and make it into a Bolus.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:170251:14"/>
                  <head>A Bolus for the Collick.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Electuary of Bay-ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes one dragme, Oil of Amber ſix drops, Oil of Aniſeed eight drops, Oil of Vitriol half a ſcruple: mingle them, and make it into a Bolus: take it in a Wafer, moiſtned in a little water, upon an empty Stomach.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Bolus for the Gout.</head>
                  <p>Take of white Julep called Mecho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>achan one dragme, Diacarthemus two dragmes, with the Syrup of Stoechados; make it into a Bolus.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Pulvis Arthriticus one ſcruple and a half, Roſin of Julep ſix grains, powder of Sarſaperilla half a ſcruple, Oil of Guaiacum four drops; and with the Syrup of the Juyce of Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorn-berryes, make it into a Bolus: take it faſting in the morning.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170251:15"/>
                  <head>A Bolus againſt the Stone.</head>
                  <p>Take Diacatholicon, Venice-Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine, waſhed in Saxafrage-water, of each half an ounce; the four greater Cool Seeds, Parſly and Fennel, of each one ſcruple, Winter Cherryes one dragme: let them be well prepared, afterwards mingled, making thereof a Bolus, and divide it into two parts for twice taking in the morning.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Bolus for the Ulcers of the Reins.</head>
                  <p>Take of Caſſia newly extracted one ounce, Mixarum two dragmes, white Thorne-Berryes two ſcruples, the Seeds of Marſh-Mallows half a dragm: add thereunto a little Sugar, and make thereof a Bolus; which is to be taken in a morning, four hours at leaſt before meat.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Bolus for the Ulcers of the Bladder.</head>
                  <p>Take of Caſſia extracted one ounce, Oxyacanth three dragmes, the four
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170251:15"/> greater Cool ſeeds two dragmes, Sugar as much as will ſuffice to make it into a Bolus, to be taken faſting.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Bolus to allay the heat of Urine.</head>
                  <p>Take of Turpentine ten times waſhed in Plantain-water half an ounce, Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catholicon three dragmes, Diarrhodon Abbatis one ſcruple, Diatri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon half a ſcruple, Diatrag. Fridg. two dragms, the beſt Sugar three ounces; make it into a Maſs, of which take the quantity of a Nutmeg twice a day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of the four greater Cool ſeeds decorticated, of each one dragme, Confectio Hamech, Caſſia extracted, of each two dragmes; Lenitium half an ounce, Turpentine waſhed ſix dragmes, Powder of Liquoriſh and Rhabarbe, of each one ſcruple, and with the Syrup of water Lillyes, make it into an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary: of which take the quantity of a Wall-nut, morning faſting, and at four of the clock in the afternoon, every day as long as it laſts.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:170251:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Cerata;</hi> or, Cerates.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Cerate for the inflammation of the Reins.</head>
                  <p>Take Oil of Roſes, Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tles, of each two dragmes; Oil of Water Lillies one ounce, red Sanders, and Mirtle-Berryes, of each one dragme; Dragons blood one dragm, the Muſilidge of Flea-bone Seed, and Quince-ſeed, of each two dragmes, Campher half a dragme, Wax one ounce. let the Oil and the Wax be waſhed a little with the Water of Purſlain, Plautain, and Womans Milk; and make thereof a Cerate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An excellent Cerate for a weak Stomach.</head>
                  <p>Take of <hi>Galens</hi> Stomachical Cerate three ounces, Nutmegs, Cinamon, of each three dragmes; ſweet Cane, Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia Moſchata, of each two ſcruples, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick two dragms, Wormwood, Mint,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170251:16"/> of each half an ounce, Aromatick VVine three dragmes, Musk one ſcrup. let thoſe be powdered that are to be beaten, and make it into a Cerate, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to art.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Diapalma two ounces, red Sanders two dragmes, Maſtick, Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs, Cinamon, Cloves, of each one dragme, Emplaſtrum Caeſaris half an ounce; and with Oil of Roſes and VVax, as much as will ſuffice to make it into a Cerate, let it be ſpead upon a Leather, adding thereupon four drops of Oil of Cinamon: let the Cerate be quilted with Sarſnet, and ſo applyed to the Stomack.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Cerate againſt Vomiting and the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becility of the Ventricle.</head>
                  <p>Take of Maſtick two dragms and half; Laudanum two dragmes; Cori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander Seed prepared, red Coral, Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>langa, Cloves, of each two ſcruples; Spikenard two dragms, Storax one dragm, Oil of VVorm-wood and Spikenard, of each a little; VVax as
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170251:17"/> much as will ſuffice, to make it up into a Cerate; which muſt be applyed to the whole Region of the Stomach.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another Cerate againſt Vomiting.</head>
                  <p>Take Maſtick two dragmes and half, Landanum two dragmes, Storax one dragme, Taccamahac, oyntment of Orange Flowers, of each three dragms, Coral one dragme, red Roſes two dragmes, Musk four grains, Oil of Mace one dragme, Oil of VVormwood and Spikenard, of each a little; caſting in as much VVax as will body it into a Cerate, and ſo apply it to the Region of the Ventricle.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Cerate for a faint and weak Stomach.</head>
                  <p>Take of Cardamoms half a dragme, Cloves one dragme, Galanga two ſcruples, Maſtick two dragmes, ſweet Cane three dragmes, Nutmegs one dragme, Storax, Landanum, Maſtick, of each half an ounce; Aloes one ſcruple, Aloes-wood one dragme, red Roſes two dragmes, Mint, VVormwood, of each two dragmes; Oil of Maſtick
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170251:17"/> and VVormwood, of each two ounces; Turpentine two dragmes, VVax one ounce and half; make hereof a Cerate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Excellent Cerate for the weakneſs of the Stomach, Spleen and Matrix.</head>
                  <p>Take red Roſes, of all the Sanders, of each one ounce; Cinamon, Cloves, Mace, Nutmegs, Galanga, Spikenard, of each two dragmes; Wormwood, Mint, Marjorane, Balme, of each one dragme; Aloes-wood two ſcruples, Gallia, Moſchata one dragme, Maſtick two ounces, Wax four ounces, Oil of Roſes one pinte and ſix ounces: let theſe be commixed into a Cerate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Cerate for the Spleen.</head>
                  <p>Take of Amoniacum two dragmes, Bdellium, Opoponax, of each one dragme; the Flowers of Melilot, Camomile, Germander, Maiden-hair, the Bark of the roots of Tama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riske, and Capers, the Seeds of Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, Lin, and Fenugreek, of each two
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170251:18"/> ſcruples; Oil of Capers two dragmes, freſh Butter one ounce and half, Wax one ounce, Ship-pitch one ounce: mingle them, and make them into a Cerate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Cerate againſt the hard ſwelling of the Womb.</head>
                  <p>Take Figs 5. boyl them in water till they become a perfect pulpe; of this pulpe take one ounce and half, Gooſe-Greaſe one ounce, Ship-pitch, yellow Wax, of each one dragme and half; Oil of Lillyes half an ounce, Diachilon Simplex two ounces: melt them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and make thereof a Cerate, to be applyed to the hard ſwelling of the Womb.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An excellent Cerate againſt Weakneſs, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammation, and pain of the Reins.</head>
                  <p>Take of white Wax four ounces, Deer-ſuet two ounces and half, freſh Buttor one ounce, Oil of Roſes two ounces and half, Oil of Water-Lillyes, Oil of ſweet Almonds, of each half an
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170251:18"/> ounce; Oil of Mirtles three dragmes, Venice Turpentine, waſhed in Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain-water two dragmes and half; Boars-greaſe waſhed in Roſe-water ſix dragmes, white-Wine four ounces, Vinegar of Roſes one ounce, Roſe-water two ounces: boyl them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther till a third part of the Wine be conſumed, then take it off from the fire, and after it hath ſtood a little, add theſe following powders: Maſtick two dragmes and a half, white and yellow Sanders two ſcruples, Amber two dragmes, Pearl one dragme, Diatrag. Fridg. one dragme, Coriander-Seed prepared with Vinegar, two ſcruples; Spodium one dragme and a half: Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate them in a hot Morter, and in the end add of the Muſilidge of Flea-bane Seed three dragmes, Campher brought into a powder three dragms; one white of an Egg beaten with womans milk: let all thoſe things be agitated in a Morter, till they be perfectly mixed and incorporated into the conſiſtency of a Cerate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:170251:19"/>
                  <head>A Cerate for the Tumors of the Paps.</head>
                  <p>Take Oil of Linſeed eight ounces, Oil of Roſes four ounces, Honey clari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied three ounces, white Wax two ounc. Bean flower four ounces, Amoniacum one ounce, Fenugreek half an ounce, Litharge three dragmes, Sage dry half an ounce: let the Gums be diſſolved in the Vinegar, and make thereof a Cerate, according to art.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Cerate for a Rupture.</head>
                  <p>Take Litharge of Gold, Lapis Hema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titis, Dragons-blood, Bole-Armoniack, Galbanum, Frankincenſe, Coſtus, Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocolla, Maſtick, Mumy, Amonia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, of each one ounce; Earth-worms, Ship-pitch, clarified Roſin, of each two dragmes; Turpentine three dragmes, the greater and leſſer Comfrey, of each ſix dragmes; red Roſes, Myrrhe, Aloes, of each half a dragme; Galls, Balanſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, round Birth-wort, of each one ounce and an half; Miſſelto of the Oake half an ounce, Mutton-ſuet one pound,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170251:19"/> red VVine and Juyce of the greater Comfrey: boyl the Juyce with the Sheep-ſuet and Gums, to the conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the VVine and Juyce; and when it is conſumed, add the VVax and Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine, and laſt of all the powders; and make thereof a Cerate.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Clyſinata;</hi> or, Glyſters.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Glyſter for a pleuriſy.</head>
                  <p>TAke of Mallows, Beets, Violets, Mercury, Barly cleanſed, of each one handful; 12 Damask Prunes: boyl them in a ſufficient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of water, to a pinte, in which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve Caſſia newly extracted, and red Sugar, of each one ounce; Oil of Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets and Linſeed, of each one ounce and half; the yolks of Eggs two, Sail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitre two ſcruples: make thereof a Glyſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:170251:20"/>
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of common Glyſter Decoction one pinte; In which diſſolve Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con one ounce; Electuary of the Juyce of Roſes three dragms; Species Hierae half a dragme; Vomiting VVine two ounces; Oil of Camomile two ounc. red Sugar one ounce: mingle it, and make thereof a Glyſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Glyſter againſt Choler.</head>
                  <p>Take of Mallows and Borage, of each one handful; the greater Cool ſeeds one ounce; the Seeds of Marſh-Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows two dragms; ſharp and tart Prunes ſix; the Flowers of Borage and water Lillyes, of each one Pugill; Damask Roſes two Pugils: make thereof a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction to a pinte; In which diſſolve Catholicon and <hi>Diaprunum Solutinum,</hi> of each ſix dragmes; Oil of Violets and red Sugar, of each two ounces: and make thereof a Glyſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:170251:20"/>
                  <head>A Glyſter againſt Flegme.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Leaves of Rue, Peni-royal, Origanum, Calamint, Sage, Hyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſop, tops of Bays, of each one handful; the Seeds of Fennel, Annis, Caraway, Cummin, reſt-Harrow, of each two dragms; the Flowers of Staechados, Roſemary, Sage, Camomile, Melilot, of each one pugil; powder of Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quintida one dragme and half: boyl theſe in Common water to a pinte; In which diſſolve Hiera Picra and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictum Laxativum, of each two dragms; Oil of Rue one ounce and half, common Salt one dragme: mingle it, and make thereof a Glyſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Glyſter againſt Melancholy.</head>
                  <p>Take Polipody of the Oake, the roots of Mallows and Marſh-Mallows, of each two ounces; the Leaves of Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litory, Drop-wort, Fumatory, Beets, Fennel, of each one handful; black Hellebore one dragme: Senna two dragms; Epithimus, Tamariske, Cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Flowers, of each one Pugil: make
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170251:21"/> thereof a Decoction; In which diſſolve Confection Hamech half an ounce; Pulvis Hali two ſcruples; Oil of Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets and Roſes, of each one ounce: mingle them, and make them into a Glyſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Aſtringent Glyſter.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Roots of the greater Comfrey, Plantain, of each half an ounc. green Galls, and Achornes, of each three dragmes; Mirtles two dragmes: boyl them in water, and in twelve ounces of the Colature, diſſolve Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia three dragmes; Starch, ſealed Earth, Gum Arabick, of each one dragme: add thereunto Juyce of Plantain two ounc. mix them for a Glyſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Glyſter againſt the pain in the Head, called Cephalalgia.</head>
                  <p>Take of Mallows, Marſh-Mallows, Violets, Beets, Barly, of each one handful; Damask Prunes 12. the four greater Cool Seeds, of each one dragm: boyl them, and add unto the Colature, Diacatholicon, Manna, of each one
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170251:21"/> ounce; Lenitive Electuary half an ounce: mingle them up into a Glyſter without Oils; for all unctious Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances do but retard the purgative fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Glyſter againſt <hi>Cephalalgia,</hi> proceeding from Flegme.</head>
                  <p>Take of Betony, Hyſſop, Hore-hound, Sage, Vervain, Bay-leaves, of each one handful; Arabian Staechados, Camomile Flowers, of each two Pugils: boyl them in water to a pinte, and to the Cola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture add two ounces of Sugar, Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaenicon three dragmes; Benedictum Laxativum two dragmes; Hony one ounce and half: mix them together for a Glyſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Glyſter againſt the Tympany and Chollick.</head>
                  <p>Take of Peny-royal, Calamint, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momile, tops of Bayes, of each one handful; Bay-berryes, the Seeds of Annis, Fennel, and Caraway, of each ſix dragmes: boyl them in a ſufficient quantity of water, till half be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed; of this Decoction take twelve
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170251:22"/> ounces; In which diſſolve red Sugar one ounce, Electuary of Bay-berries, <hi>Hiera Logadij, Hiera Picra,</hi> of each half an ounce; Oil of Rue one ounce and half, Salt-Peter one dragme: mingle them into a Glyſter, and to be injected before meals.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Aſtringent Glyſter to the Ulcers of the Inteſtines.</head>
                  <p>Take of Horſe-tail, Plantain, Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons ſeal, Shepherds Purſe, of each one handful: boyl them in burnt Milk to twelve ounces; and in the Colature diſſolve two whites of Eggs: the beſt Bole one dragme and half; the Juyce of white Poppy one ounce: mingle them all together, and make thereof a Glyſter. Let it be given before meals, or three full hours after.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170251:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Collyria;</hi> or, Collyries, <hi>i. e.</hi> Waters for the Eyes.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Collyry againſt <hi>Ophthalmia, i. e.</hi> an Inflammation in the Eye.</head>
                  <p>TAke Muſiledge of Flea-bane Seed, extracted in Roſe-water, Gum Thraganth and Arabick, of each two dragmes; the white of an Egg well beaten: mingle them, and make thereof a Collyry; which muſt be uſed morning and night.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>A Collyry corroborating the Eyes againſt</hi> Ophthalmia.</head>
                  <p>Take Tutty prepared two dragmes; Camphor one ſcruple: let them be finely powdered, and with the Water of Roſes and Fennel, make thereof a Collyry, which uſe morning and night.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:170251:23"/>
                  <head>A Collyry for watry Eyes,</head>
                  <p>Take waſhed Ceruſs, Sarcocolla, Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, Olibanum, of each two dragmes; the Stones of Mirabolans burnt, red Coral, and white, of each one dragme; Pearl half a dragme, the Juyce of Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granates boyled till half be conſumed, as much as will ſuffice; make thereof a Collyry.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Collyry againſt a cold Rheume in the Eyes.</head>
                  <p>Take of Frankincenſe, Maſtick, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs-Nuts, Myrrhe, Aloes, of each two dragmes; Tutty prepared, Sarcocolla, of each one dragme and half, Dragons<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blood, white Thorn-berryes, red Roſes, of each one ounce: let all theſe be mingled together, and with Fennel water make them into a Colly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; which drop into the Eyes morning and night.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:170251:23"/>
                  <head>A Collyry againſt Inflammations, Ulcers, and Rheumes of the Eyes.</head>
                  <p>Take the whites of Eggs well beaten two ounces; Roſe-water and Plantain-water, of each two ounces; Juyce of Apples clarifyed half an ounce: mingle them for a Collyry, which muſt be often dropped into the Eyes, at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Inflammation: and if there be any pain that accompanies it, then add Troches, Albi Rhaſis, without Opium, or with Opium; If the pain be ſharp, one dragme: ſtrain it, and uſe it as before; there may be alſo added a little of Womans milk, to aſſwage the pain, or the blood of Pigeons freſh and newly let out; or the Decoction of the Seeds of white Poppyes, with a little Saffron to correct it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Collyry againſt the Dimneſs, Watryneſs, Redneſs, and Itching of the Eyes.</head>
                  <p>Take of Sugar Candy, Hepaticks, Aloes, of each two dragmes; Lapis Caliminaris prepared five grains; Camphor one ſcruple; white Wine,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170251:24"/> Roſe-water, Eye-bright water, Salen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine, and Vervine water, of each two dragmes: mingle them, and make them into a Collyry.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another of the ſame Nature.</head>
                  <p>Take Tutty prepared, powder of Pearl, of each half a dragme; powder of Aloes one ſcruple: make of theſe ſmall Pills, which infuſe in Roſe-water, Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel or Vervine; and ſo let it be drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped into the Eyes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Collyry for the ſcowring of Ulcers, and the diſperſing of the whites in the Eyes.</head>
                  <p>Take Syrup of Roſes, Sugar Candy one dragme; Harts-horn, and Goats-horn burnt, and finely powdered, and well waſhed in Roſe-water, of each half a dragme; the water of Salendine and Fennel, of each two ounces: mingle them well together.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:170251:24"/>
                  <head>A Collyry appeaſing pain.</head>
                  <p>Take the water of Violets and Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, of each half an ounce; Troch Albi Raſis with Opium, the whites of Eggs, the Juyce of Fenugreek, waſhed in Roſe-water, of each half an ounce: mingle them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Collyry cleanſing the Eyes.</head>
                  <p>Take of Frankincenſe, Myrrhe, of each one ſcruple; Tutty prepared, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony waſhed, of each half a ſcruple; and with the Juyce of Salendine, dryed in the ſhade, make thereof a Collyry.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Collyry for ſuch as are peſtered with the ſmall Pox.</head>
                  <p>Take of Eye-bright water one pint and half; put it upon the fire, and when it boyles, caſt into it Liquoriſh very well bruiſed two ounces: remove it from the fire, letting it ſtand till it's cold: then adding thereunto the whites of three Eggs well beaten, with two ounces of Plantain-water, make there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a Collyry.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:170251:25"/>
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Subſtract a thin Muſilidge from Quince-ſeeds, with white Roſe-water, hanging therein a ſmall Nodule of Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron, to give it a tincture, and let it be dropped by degrees into the Eyes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Condita;</hi> or, Condites, or Opiates.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A cordial Condite.</head>
                  <p>TAke of the Conſerve of Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary Flowers, Bugloſs, Borage, Succory, Maiden-hair, of each two dragmes; Citron-Pill condited one dragme and half; ſpecies Diamosk Dulcis, Diarrhodon Abatis, the three Sanders, of each half a dragme; Leaves of Gold Nu. 6. and with white Sugar, make it up into a condite, covering it over with Gold: the doſe is the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of a Nut, when the Stomack is ill.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:170251:25"/>
                  <head>A Corroborating Condite.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Conſerve of Water Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, Bugloſs, Roſes, Citron-pill Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited, of each half an ounce; powder of Gemmes compound; Diambre Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>margaritan. Fridg. of each half a ſcrup. of the Bone in the heart of a Hart, the Seeds of Citrul, and Carduus, Tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till, of each one ſcruple; the ſhavings or Filings of an Unicornes Horn ſeven grains, Bezoar Stone ſix grains, five Leaves of Gold, with as much white Sugar as will ſuffice, as will make it up into a Condite.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A reſtorative Condite.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Conſerve of the Flowers of Sage, Roſemary, of each half an ounc. Confection of Alkermes half a dragm; Species Aromaticum Roſatum, of the fragments of precious ſtones, both the Corals, of each half a dragm; Oxgya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canty a dragme and half; Conſerve of the Flowers of Bugloſs and Borage, of each one dragme and half; Oil of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon three drops: mingle them in a white Marble Morter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:170251:26"/>
                  <head>An Antidotive Condite, or preſervative against Infection.</head>
                  <p>Take of Mithridate two ſcruples; Venice Treacle one ſcruple; Conſerve of Wood-ſorrel, and Mary-golds, of each one ounce; balm half an ounce; Mirabolans Condited, Citron-pill, and Lemon-pill Condited, of each ſix dragmes; the powder of Setwell, and Tormentil, of each two ſcruples; and with the Syrup of Wood-ſorel, and white Sugar, make it into a Condite; taking the quantity of a Wall-nut, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry morning faſting.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Decoctiones;</hi> or, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coctions.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Decoction against a hot burning Feaver.</head>
                  <p>TAke of Succory with the Roots, Sorrel, Endive, of each one handful; the four greater Cool-ſeeds,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170251:26"/> of each one dragme; Graſs roots and Sparagraſs macerated in Vinegar, of each three dragmes: boyl them in a ſufficient quantity of water, till it comes to a pinte: add unto the clear Cola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, white Sugar, and Juyce of Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, of each three ounces: or in the end of the Decoction, add ſharp Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar and Hony well ſcummed, of each three ounces; white Sanders two ſcrup. mingle them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another for the ſame purpoſe.</head>
                  <p>Take Sorrel, Wood-ſorrel, Borage, Violet Leaves, Straw-berry Leaves, and Endive, of each one handful; Harts-horn, and Ivory ſhavings, of each half an ounce; Scorzonery roots one ounce; well bruiſed Succory root half an ounc. Citron-ſeed two ſcruples: boyl all theſe in three pints of Barly-water, till a third part be conſumed; add there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto Juyce of Lemmons two ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulls: ſtrain it, and to the Colature add Aquae Cordialis Fridg. Saxoniae four ounces: mingle them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:170251:27"/>
                  <head>A Decoction against Choler.</head>
                  <p>Take the Roots of Garden Endive, Bugloſs, Liqueriſh, the five opening Roots, of each half an ounce: Maiden-hair, and Violet Flowers, of each one handful; the Seeds of Smallidge, and Fennel, Lavender, Egrimony, of each two dragmes; Maſtick one ſcruple, Raiſins ſtoned four handfuls; Barly cleanſed one handful: Tamarinds and Damask prunes, of each one ounce and half: mingle them, and make them into a Decoction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A pectoral Decoction against a Pleuriſie.</head>
                  <p>Take Raiſins ſtoned, Liqueriſh, of each half a dragme; the Seeds of Annis and Fennel, of each two dragms; Figgs Nu. vj. Dates one ounce; Barly clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed two handfuls, Hyſſop, Maiden-hair, of each two handfuls; Florentine Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris one ounce: make a Decoction thereof, till half of the Liquor be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:170251:27"/>
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Coltsfoot, Maiden-hair, Lung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, Liverwort, Garden Scurvigraſs, of each one handful; Raiſins ſtoned four ounces, Liqueriſh half an ounce, Bears tooth raſped two dragmes, Stone-Horſe Dung one ounce, Figgs three ounces: make of theſe a Decoction in ſpring water, boyling them till half the water be conſumed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Decoction againſt Flegme.</head>
                  <p>Take Hyſſop, Betony, Hore-hound, Origanum, the Leaves of Bayes, and Roſemary, of each one Pugill, Guai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acum, (An Indian-wood ſo called) groſly powdered: Saſſafras, Sarſaperilla, of each one ounce, the Seeds of Fennel and Annis, Juniper-berryes, of each two dragmes: the roots of Fennel and Perſly, Maiden-hair, of each half an ounce; Orris three dragmer, Hony two ounces nad half: mingle them, and boyl them in water, till half be conſumed, and afterwards repoſe it for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:170251:28"/>
                  <head>A Decoction againſt Melancholy.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Flowers of Borage and Bugloſs, of each one ounce; Polipody, <hi>i. e.</hi> Epithimus, Staechados, Maiden-hair, Raiſins ſtoned, the Bark of the roots of Capers, the Bark of Tamarisk, the Bark of Aſh, Fumatory, the flowers of Camomile, of each one ounce: boyl theſe in three pints of water, till half be conſumed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Carminative Decoction.</head>
                  <p>Take of the flowers of Camomile, Staechados, Rue, Melilot, tops of Bayes, of each half a handful; the ſeeds of Annis, Fennel, Caraway, Bay-berries bruiſed, the ſeeds of Dill, Ladies Roſe, and Rue, of each three dragmes: boyl all theſe in four pints of Water till half be conſumed, and ſo preſerve it for Glyſters.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Decoction for a Cancer.</head>
                  <p>Take of freſh water Crabs Calcined, and beaten into very fine powder two
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170251:28"/> dragmes, Self-heal, Sanicle, Bugle, Fluellen, of each one handful: boyl them in three pints of water till half be conſumed: in the end adding Crabs eyes and claws gloſly pulverized, of each two dragmes; white Wine one pinte: then ſtrain it for future or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Decoction againſt the Venereal Dolors.</head>
                  <p>Take the Raſpings of Guaiacum four ounces, the Bark of the ſame one ounc. Infuſe them in four pints of Fountain water, according to art: afterwards boyl them till half be conſumed; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding towards the end of the Decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Maiden-hair, Succory, Borage, Carduus, of each one handful; Raiſins ſtoned, Liqueriſh, of each three dragms; Melon-ſeed two dragmes: boyl them, and after one Ebulution ſtrain it: of this Decoction, take half a pint warm in hemorning, and ſweat after it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:170251:29"/>
                  <head>A Decoction against Seroſe or watriſh Humors.</head>
                  <p>Take of Lignum Guaiacum two ounc. Sarſaperilla one ounce and half, Saſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fras half an ounce: let them be infuſed in four pints of Fountain water; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards boyled till half be conſumed, and let the Colature be kept in a glaſs, taking every morning ſeven ounces very warm.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another of the ſame Nature.</head>
                  <p>Take of Sarſaperilla cut ſmall and cleanſed from his Filaments three ounc. Infuſe it in Fountain water eight pints, for the ſpace of eighteen hours: then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dd thereunto Gum Guaiacum two ounces; boyl them tillhalf be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed: let the Colature be put into Bottles, and drink thereof eight ounces in the morning, ſweating after it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:170251:29"/>
                  <head>A Decoction for the French Diſeaſe.</head>
                  <p>Take of Guaiacum eight ounces, the Bark of the ſame, Sarſaperilla, of each four ounces: bruiſe them very ſmall, and infuſe them in a pot cloſe covered, in twelve pints of water; then boyl them till a third part be conſumed, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereunto Liqueriſh three ounc. Raiſins ſtoned two ounces, Harts-horn one ounce, Gum Guaiacum half an ounce: ſtrain it, and let the Colature be preſerved in Glaſs Bottles, drinking of it for ordinary drink.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A purging Decoction of the ſame Nature.</head>
                  <p>Take Sarſaperilla, Lignum Guaiacum, of each three ounces; the Bark of the ſame two ounces, Polipody, Epithimus, of each one ounce and half: Infuſe them, and boyl them in ſix pints of Fountain water, till half be conſumed; and at the end of the Decoction add Alexandrian Senna two ounces; ſtrain it, and let the Colature be preſerved in Bottles cloſe ſtopt, drinking there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170251:30"/> half a pint every other morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Decoction opening obſtructions.</head>
                  <p>Take of the five Opening Roots, Liqueriſh, Roſe Leaves, the middle Bark of Aſh, the Bark of the Root of Capers, of each one ounce; Orris Root, freſh Cinamon, ſweet Cane, of each half an ounce; Maiden-hair, Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, Hyſſop Carduus, Hore-hound, Fennel, Egrimony, of each one hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, the Seeds of Annis, Ladies Roſe, and Smallidge, of each two dragmes; Senna picked and cleanſed three ounc. dry Soldanella half an ounce, the Seed of dwarfe Elder, Gummeous Turbith ſix dragmes, Broom Flowers, Tamaris, of each one Pugil: boyl them in water where ſteel hath been quenched three pints, to which add about the end of the Decoction half a pint of white-Wine: ſtrain it, and with red Sugar as much as will ſuffice, dulcify it, and it may be made into an Apozeme by adding ſpecies Aromaticum Roſatum.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:170251:30"/>
                  <head>Another Decoction much of the ſame Nature.</head>
                  <p>Take Graſs roots, Succory roots, Bugloſs and Aſparagraſs, of each one ounce; the middle Bark of the roots of Capers and Tamaris, of each three dragmes; the Leaves of Borage and Bugloſs, of each two handfuls; Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rach, Maiden-hair, of each one hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, Polipody two ounces, Raiſins ſtoned one ounce, the Seeds of Annis and Fennel, of each two ounces, the roots of Liqueriſh ſix dragms, the three Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial Flowers, of each one Pugil: firſt infuſe them, and then boyl them in a ſufficient quantity of clear water to three pints: ſtrain it, and clarify the Colature; which may be made into an Apozeme, by adding ſpecies Diatrion Santalon three dragmes, and Syrup of Borage three ounces.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Decoction againſt Melancholy.</head>
                  <p>Take Sparagraſs roots, Hops, the middle Bark of Elder and Aſh, Succory root, of each one ounce; Scabiouſe,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170251:31"/> Egrimony, Borage, Bugloſs, Fumatory, Dropwort, Maiden-hair, of each one handful; ſweet Prunes, Nu. vij. Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed two dragmes, Succory Flowers one Pugil: boyl them all in Whey, a ſufficient quantity, till it come to a pint and half.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Decoction gently purging Sordid Humors.</head>
                  <p>Take of Rhabarbe, Senna, of each one dragme and half; Spikenard half a ſcruple: Infuſe them in a ſufficient quantity of white-Wine upon hot Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, ſtrain out four ounces, add to the Colature Diacatholicon three dragms, Confectio Hamech one dragme, Juyce of Roſes half a dragme: mingle them for a Decoction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Decoction gently purging Choler.</head>
                  <p>Take Senna half an ounce, Pulpe of Tamarinds two dragms, the Cordial Flowers, of each one Pugill; ſweet Fennel Seed one dragme: boyl them in a ſufficient quantity of pectoral De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, adding of the beſt Rhabarbe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170251:31"/> one dragme, Chebulan Mirabalens half a dragme, Ginger, Squinant, of each eight grains; Citron Pill one ſcruple: ſtrain out three ounces and an half; add thereunto Manna half an ounce, Syrup of Roſes with Agarick half an ounce, Oil of Sulphur three drops.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another much of the ſame vertue, recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the blood, purging Melancholy, and removing the obſtructions of the Spleen.</head>
                  <p>Take Senna one ounce and half, Epithimus half an ounce, Polipody of the Oake half an ounce, Rhabarbe two dragmes, Agarick one dragme and half, ſweet Fennel Seed three dragms, Cara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way two dragmes, the Flowers of Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets ſix Pugils, tops of Borage two handfuls, Ruſſetins in Number two Decorticated, Prunes and Currans, of each three ounces: boyl them and infuſe them in a ſufficient quantity of water; take of the Colature ſeven ounces, divide it into two parts: in the firſt diſſolve Syr. Magiſt. add Melanch. one ounce, Juyce of Oranges three dragmes, the compound water of Balm
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170251:32"/> half a dragme: take it in the morning early: three dayes after, take the ſecond part, to which add Diaphaenicon two dragmes, Syrup of Violets one ounce, Juyce of Oranges one ſpoonful: mingle them. <hi>But indeed theſe rather ought to be ranked in the Tribe of Potions, then De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coctions.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Decoction purging Melancholy.</head>
                  <p>Take Dropwort, Borage, of each one handful and half; Raiſins ſtoned, Epithimus, Polipody, Indian Mirabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens one dragme and half, Senna two dragmes: make a Decoction, and to the expreſſion add Caſſia one ounce, Confectio Hamech two dragmes, Syrup of Roſes one ounce: mingle them and make it into a Hauſtus, and to be taken in the morning; ordering the Body as the accuſtomed manner is in all Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Decoction againſt the Dropſy.</head>
                  <p>Take Lignum Sanctum one pound and half, China root one ounce, Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain water ſixteen pints, white-Wine
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170251:32"/> two pints; to which add the roots of Aſparagraſs, Fennel, Smallidg, Graſs, Parſly, Butchers Broom, Madder, and Orris Roots, of each two ounces; the Roots of Aſarabacca, the Bark of the Roots of Tormentil, Tamaris and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, of each one ounce; Egrimony, both Succories, Ceterach, or ſpleen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, and Maiden-hair, of each one handful; Soldanella one handful and half, the ſeed of Annis, Biſhop-weed, of each three dragmes; Melon-ſeed bruiſed one ounce, 20 Raiſins ſtoned, Choice Cinamon three dragmes, red Cicers two Pugills: make a Decoction of theſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ill one part thereof be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed; then ſtrain it, and to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lature add yellow Sanders, Cinamon and Orris root, of each one ounce: <hi>fiat Decoctio.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Decoction againſt Droptical Humors.</head>
                  <p>Take Lignum Guaiacum half a pound, the Leaves of Borage, Bugloſs, Camo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile, Hyſſop, Sage, Parſly, of each one handful and half, Egrimony two hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls, the Roots of Fennel, and Parſly,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170251:33"/> the Pith from within being taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, of each two; Orris root two ounc. Liqueriſh four ounces, Polipody of the Oake three ounces, ſweet Fennel ſeed four ounces, Bay-berryes two ounces, Cinamon, Nutmeg, Ginger, Mace, of each two dragmes: let the roots, the ſpecies, and the ſeeds be bruiſed, and put into an earthen Pipkin, with thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen pints of Water, and four pints of white Wine; covering it cloſe, putting it into a Kettle with water, that it may ſtand in a Bath, with a good fire under it, for the ſpace of twenty four hours: afterwards make an Expreſſion, and take of the Colature, Mornings, Noons, and Nights.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Decoction provoking Urine.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Bark or rind of the Roots of Fennel, Parſly, Butcher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broom, of each two ounces; Ciperus half an ounce, the Seeds of Biſhop-weed, Coriander, Parſly, Maſtick, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, Annis, Cardamoms, Cummin, of each one dragme: boyl them, and add unto the Colature as much Sugar as will ſuffice to ſweeten it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:170251:33"/>
                  <head>A Decoction againſt the Inflammation and Opilation of the Liver.</head>
                  <p>Take of Borage, Bugloſs, Violets, Egrimony, Endive, Succory, Fumatory, of each one handful; the roots of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly and Fennel, of each one ounce; Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins ſtoned four ounces, Dates one ounce, Mace three dragmes, Cinamon half an ounce, Aniſeed two dragmes, Fountain-Water, and white-Wine, of each three pints; Sugar one pound, Liqueriſh one ounce: mingle them, and boyl them, till half be conſumed: then ſtrain it; and of the Colature after it is ſetled, take before meals three ounces, for ten days together.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Decoction againſt ſuch Diſeaſes as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from humidity.</head>
                  <p>Take Lignum Guaiacum ſix ounces, the Bark of the ſame two ounces, Sarſape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilla two ounces and half, Chiny Root one ounce, ſowre Dock-root one ounce, Rhabarbe one dragme, Turbith half an ounce, Agarick half an ounce, Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pody, Liqueriſh, of each four ounces:
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170251:34"/> the Pith of the Seeds of Meadow-Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron half an ounce, the Bark of Capers-root one ounce, the five opening roots, of each half an ounce; Sage three hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls, Romane Wormwood one handful and an half, Anniſeed two ounces, Hony one pound, Cinamon ſix ounces, white-Wine four pints, Fountain-water ſixteen pints: Infuſe them a whole night, and boyl them for a good ſpace: afterwards ſtrain them, and let the Colature be preſerved in a veſſel cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly covered: and take thereof every morning four ounces faſting, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Dinner and Supper three ounces: and after that the Decoction is ſpent, boyl the ingredients over again, with the ſame quantity of Water as before; adding Wine two pints, and Hony of Roſes two pound; of which take the ſame quantity as before: only this lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Decoction muſt be drunk for thirty dayes together; And every day for ten of the firſt, to ſweat one hour: and if the Body be coſtive, in the taking of the aforeſaid Decoction; then uſe this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing mixture. Take of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Decoction three ounces, Manna one ounce, Syrup of Roſes one ounce,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170251:34"/> Confectio Hamek two dragmes: min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle them into a Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtus.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Electuaria;</hi> or, Electua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary againſt the Epilepſy.</head>
                  <p>TAke freſh Pellitory half a pound; ſcummed Hony three pound, Ginger one ounce; Cloves, Nutmegs, Cubebs, of each five dragmes: mingle them, and make them into an Electuary.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of the powder of Pyony-root two ounces, of the powder of a Mans Skull two dragmes, Elkes Claw one dragme; the Bird Jay dryed and burnt one ounce and half, Nutmeg and Mace, of each two ſcruples; Agarick ſix drag. Ginger four ſcruples: Let all theſe be finely powdered, and mixed with four ounces of white Sugar; diſſolved in
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170251:35"/> Aquae Langii: make it up into an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, adding thereunto four or five drops of Spirit of Amber: take of this every morning the quantity of a Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary for the Epilepſy, and Suffo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Matrix.</head>
                  <p>Take of the foecula of Briony-Root half a pound, Hony, Raiſons ſtoned, of each three pound; baked Squils, Pine-Kernels bruiſed, of each one ounce and half; Nutmeg, Cinamon, Mace, Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Cardamomes, of each two dragms; Cloves, Long Pepper, Staechados, of each one dragme and half; the Seeds of Reſt-harrow, Salgem, Gallia Moſchata; of each one dragme; Spicknard half a dragme, Agarick three dragmes: let it be given after ſix times taking, from two dragmes to three.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another of the ſame Nature.</head>
                  <p>Take of Pellitory, Reſt-Harrow, Stae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chados, of each ten dragmes; Agarick five dragmes, Cardamoms, round Birth-wort, Liqueriſh, the Seeds of Balſamit,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170251:35"/> Piony, of each two dragmes; the Juyce of Squils and Hony, of each equal parts: Let them all be cocted to the Conſiſtency of an Electuary.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary for the Reins and the Bladder.</head>
                  <p>Take Diaphaenicum two dragmes, Juyce of Roſes one dragme and half, Caſſia half a drachm, Rhabarb half a dragme, Venice-Turpentine waſhed in Roſe-water, Conſerve of Violets, of each three dragms; Treacle one dragme and half, Diamargarit Frig. Diarrhodon Abbatis, Diambres, Diatrion Piperion; of each one ſcruple; of all the Saunders half a dragme, Citron-pill one dragme, Sugar as much as will ſuffice to make it into an Electuary.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary purging the Bladder, and allaying the heat of Urine.</head>
                  <p>Take Turpentine well waſhed in the Water of Marſh-Mallows, Caſſia newly extracted, of each one ounce and half; Pulp of Tamarinds ſix dragms, Troches Gordonii, Melon-ſeed Excorticated, of each three dragmes, Cucumber and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170251:36"/> Pepon-Seeds, of each two dragmes; Rhabarbe thin cut, and macerated in Plaintain water two dragmes: beat them together into an Electuary, with Syrup of Water Lillyes, as much as will ſuffice: of which take three quarters of an ounce every morning.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary cleanſing the Reins, corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a Gonorrhea.</head>
                  <p>Take Diacatholicon Lenitivum, of each one ounce; Confection Hamech ſix dragm. Species Diatraganth, Frig. three dragmes, Rhabarbe finely pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered one dragme, Liquoriſh, Aniſeed, of each one ſcruple; waſhed Turpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine one ounce and half, Caſſia three dragmes: and with Syrup of Marſh-Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows make it into an Electuary. The Doſe is the quantity of a Nutmeg, twice in a day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary proper for thoſe who labour under the French Diſeaſe.</head>
                  <p>Take of Aloes-wood, Lignum, Guaia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, Sarſaperilla in powder, of each half an ounce; the Seeds of Fennel, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duus,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170251:36"/> Citron, of each two dragmes; the Roots of Setwel, Birth-wort, and Gentian Cinamon, of each one dragm. and half, Species Diatrion, Santal-Diar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhodon, Abatis, of each one dragme and half; Mithridate half an ounce, Conſerve of Succory, and Borage, of each half an ounce; and with half a pound of Syrup of Succory, make it into an Electuary: of this, take the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of a Nutmeg twice in a day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary purging both the Reins and Bladder.</head>
                  <p>Take Caſſia newly Extracted from the Cane half an ounce, powder of Rharbarb half a dragme, Agnus Caſtus ſeed in powder two ſcruples, Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licon half an ounce, Venice Turpentine waſhed in Roſe-water one ounce; mingle them: take of this two dragm. wrapt in a wet wafer twice a day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary againſt the Stone.</head>
                  <p>Take of the four great Cool ſeeds, of each half an ounce; the Seeds of Purſlain, Endive, white Poppy, of each
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170251:37"/> one dragme, powder of Marſh-Mallow Root two dragmes, Saxafrage, Grum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel-Seed, of each one dragme and half; Winter Cherryes, Senna, of each half an ounce; Sugar diſſolved in Saxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage and Parſly Water four ounces: make it into an Electuary; take the quantity of a Nutmeg three times a day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary againſt the pains of the Bladder and Reins.</head>
                  <p>Take Venice-Turpentine, Caſſia lately drawn, of each one ounce; Juyce of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queriſh, Marſh-mallow-ſeed, of each two dragms; Plantain-ſeed half a drag. Winter Cherryes one dragme and an half, the Seeds of Melon, Cucumber and Gourd, of each one dragme; and with a ſufficient quantity of Syrup of Marſh-mallows, make it up into an Electuary, of which take the quantity of a Cheſnut three times a day, firſt Morning, Noon and Night.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:170251:37"/>
                  <head>An Electuary against the hard Labour of a woman in Travel.</head>
                  <p>Take Myrrhe, Caſtor, Storax, of each one ſcruple; Savine one ſcruple and half: Cynamon, Caſſia-lignea, of each one drachm: Amber three drachms. Let theſe be finely powdered, and mixed with a ſufficient quantity of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar diſſolved in Savine-water, to make it up into an Electuary. The Doſe is a drachm or a half.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Heart-chearing Electuary.</head>
                  <p>Take of Red-Roſes, Aloes-wood, of each half an ounce: Mace, Nutmeg, Gallia-Moſchata, Cardamomes both the ſorts, of each one drachm: Cyperus two drachms and an half: Cloves, Aſara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacca, Maſtich, Spikenard, of each one drachm and half: Moſch ſeven grains, Sugar diſſolved in Cordial-water, and Syrup of Cynamon, of each equal parts, as much as will ſuffice to make it up into an Electuary. The Doſe is the quantity of a Nutmeg.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:170251:38"/>
                  <head>An Electuary againſt a ſharp Looſneſs.</head>
                  <p>Take old Conſerve of Roſes two ounces, Pulvis Diamarg. frig. one drachm and an half, Bole-armeniack, Red Coral, of each two drachms: Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar diſſolved in Cynamon-water, as much as will ſuffice.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Rhabarb dryed well by the fire and powdered two drachms, Pome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granate-pill and flowers, of each one drachm: Maſtich and Olibanum, of each one ſcruple: dryed Turpentine in fine powder three drachms, Conſerve of old Red-Roſes three ounces; and with ſyrup of Quinces make it into an Electuary. The Doſe is two drachms three or four times a day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary againſt the pain of the Cholick.</head>
                  <p>Take of Agarick half an ounce, the roots of Orris and round Birthwort, Hyſſop, Maſtich, Squinant, Carpobalſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170251:38"/> Aniſeed, of each half a drachm: Gummeous Turbith finely powdered and ſifted, the weight of them all; and with honey as much as will ſuffice to incorporate it into an Electuary. The Doſe is half an ounce.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>An Electuary against the pain occaſioned from the ſtopping of the ſmall guts, termed by Phyſicians</hi> Iliaco Paſſio.</head>
                  <p>Take of Cumin-ſeed, Aſſa-foetida, Caraway, Birthwort, the flowers of Chamomile, Queens crown, Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, Agarick, of each ten drachms: the three Peppers, and Opium, of each one drachm: Saffron, Carpobalſamum, Squinant, Cynamon, of each two drach<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the roots of Aſarabacca, and Gentian, of each one drachm. Let theſe be pulverized and ſifted; and with a ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup made of honey, and the decoction of Squinant, Queens crown, and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momile, make thereof an Electuary. The Doſe whereof is two drachms, or three, or four, according to the conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution and quality of the perſon taking it; which muſt be diſſolved in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction of Aniſeed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:170251:39"/>
                  <head>An Electuary diſpelling Winde, and windy vapours.</head>
                  <p>Take Maſtich, Aniſeed, Ginger, of each one drachm: beſt Turbith two drachms; and with honey ſcummed, make it into an Electuary. The Doſe of it is two drachms.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary for the Fits of the Cholick and the Stone.</head>
                  <p>Take Turbith, Acorus, of each ſix drachms: Cumin, Caraway, of each one drachm and half: Agarick, Orris, Birthwort, of each ſix drachms: Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganum, Hſſyop, of each three drachms: Maſtich, Squinant, of each one drachm. Let theſe be powdered and ſifted; and with honey clarified made into an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary. The Doſe hereof is two drachms drunk in a glaſs of burnt Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary for ſuch as cannot hold their Water.</head>
                  <p>Take dryed Spodium, Aloes-wood,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170251:39"/> the ſeeds of Purſlain, Gum-Arabick, Gum-Thraganth, Barberries, Turbith, Endive-ſeed, Bole-Armeniack of each four drachms; and with honey of Roſes make it into an Electuary. The Doſe of it is one drachm every mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary against the Plague.</head>
                  <p>Take of all the Sanders, Lignum-Aloes, Cynamon, Nutmegs, of each one drachm: round Birthwort, the roots of Tormentil, Storax, of each two ſcruples: the flowers of Roſema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Bugloſs, Borage, Violets, of each half a pugil: Enula-campane, Angelico, of each half a drachm: the fragments of the precious ſtones, Pearl, Ivory, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, Gallia Moſchata, of each half a ſcruple: Camphyr ſix grains, Conſerve of the flowers of Sage, Roſemary, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, of each two ounces; and with the ſyrup of condited Citron, make it up into an Electuary. The Doſe is the quantity of a Cheſnut in the morning.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:170251:40"/>
                  <head>An Electuary to revive the ſpirits.</head>
                  <p>Take ſpecies Diambrae, de Gemmis, Diamoſch. dulcis, of each two ſcruples: Laetificans Galeni one drachm, Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio de Hyacinthio one ounce, Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio Alkermes three ounces, Amber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>griſe four grains, two condited Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs; and with ſyrup of Gilliflowers make it up into an Electuary. The Doſe is one drachm in a cup of burnt Claret.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Preſervative.</head>
                  <p>Take Manus Chriſti perlat. one ounce, Saphyr, Smaragd, of the bone in the heart of a Hart, Saffron, Amber, ſhavings of Ivory, of each half a drach. ſpecies de Gemmis, Diamarg. calid. Diarrhodon Abbatis, Aromaticum Roſatum, of each one drachm and half: Conſerve of Roſes, Citron-pill condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, Conſerve of Sorrel, Bugloſs, Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, of each one ounce: Sugar one ounce and half. Make it into an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary with ſyrup of Cynamon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:170251:40"/>
                  <head>An Electuary or Antidote againſt the Plague.</head>
                  <p>Take an Egge, out of which take the white; and put into the place where the white was, one ſcruple of Saffron; which dry in the Egge ſo long, till it may be powdered; adding thereunto Tormentil, Setwel, Angelico, Dittany, round Birthwort, of each two drach. Sealed Earth one drachm, Bole-Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niack, Citron-pill, Myrrhe, dry Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, dry Rue, Bugloſs and Borage-flowers, Pearl, of each half a ſcruple: Treacle fourteen ounces; which, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with Carduus-water, make into the conſiſtencie of an Electuary. The Doſe is one drachm.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>An Electuary againſt the Flix</hi> Lienteria.</head>
                  <p>Take Pearl one drachm, Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe half a drachm, Maſtich one drach. and half, Nutmeg, Mace, of each half a drachm: red Coral, Bole-Armeniack, Lapis Haematitis, of each two drachms. Make thereof a fine powder; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards commix it with ſyrup of Mint
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170251:41"/> one ounce. Let it ſtand in a warm place for three hours; afterwards, adde Conſerve of old Roſes three ounces, and with ſyrup of Mint make it into an Electuary, covering it over with leaf-gold. The Doſe is about the quantity of a Nutmeg at a time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>An Electuary for the Looſneſs</hi> Diarrhaea.</head>
                  <p>Take of the meat or medulla of Quinces condited one ounce, preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Citron half an ounce, red Coral, Pomegranate-pill, of each three drach. Acacia one ounce, Diamargarit. frigid. two drachms, Myrcle-ſeed one drachm: Let them all be powdered, and made into an Electuary with ſyrup of Quinces.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary for the obſtruction of the Liver.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Conſerve of the roots of Smallage, Conſerve of the flowers of Succory, Maidenhair, of each half an ounce: the ſpecies of Diarrhodon Abbatis, Diatrionſantalon, of each two drachms: Troches of Egrimony
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170251:41"/> one drachm; and with ſyrupo Byzanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no make it up into an Electuary: of which take half an ounce for a Doſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary for the impotencie of Coiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; or rather, to provoke to Venery.</head>
                  <p>Take of Diaſatyrion three ounces, preſerved Ginger, the brains of Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows and Pigeons, Pine-kernels, Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtack-Nuts, Nettle-ſeed, Pepper, Cyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Rocket-ſeed, of each one drach. and with the ſyrup of Ginger condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, make it up into an Electuary; of which eat at pleaſure.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary provoking the Tearms.</head>
                  <p>Take Borax two drachms, Caſſia-wood two ſcruples, Saffron three grains, Troches of Myrrhe one drachm, Trife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae magnae ſine opio two ſcruples, Juni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-berries one drachm, Venice-Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle two drachms, ſyrup of Mugwort half an ounce, Sugar as much as will ſuffice to make it up into an Electuary.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:170251:42"/>
                  <head>An Electuary to ſtay the Courſes.</head>
                  <p>Take Diarrhodon Abbatis half a drachm, Diacynamomi one ſcruple, Diacorallii half a ſcruple, Balanſtians one drachm, Bole-Armeniack, two ſcruples, ſealed Earth half a drachm, Conſerve of Comfrey, old Roſes, of each half an ounce; Sugar as much as will ſuffice: mingle them, and make it up into an Electuary; of which take half an ounce for a Doſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>An Electuary againſt the Falling-ſickneſs, called</hi> Morbum Comitialem.</head>
                  <p>Take Diacori three ounces, ſpecies Diamoſchi, Aloes-wood, of each half a drachm, Cubebs ſix grains: Piony-ſeeds, Miſsleto, Mans ſcull prepared, Peacocks dung, of each half an ounce: Conſerve of Bugloſs one ounce, Sage half an ounce. Mingle them well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Of this take the quantity of a N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> three or four times a day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:170251:42"/>
                  <head>An Electuary againſt the Palſey.</head>
                  <p>Take Lavender-tops dry one ounce, Spike half an ounce. Let them be cut and bruiſed, and finely beaten, and with half an ounce of Sugar diſſolved in Betony-water, adding thereunto Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon ſix drachms, Mace two drachms, Cloves one drachm. Mingle them, and make them into an Electuary, with ſyrup of Stoechados. The Doſe is two drachms.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another of the ſame vertue, to prevent it.</head>
                  <p>Take of Acorus one drachm, Ginger two ounces and an half, Peper, Pelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, of each one ounce: Caſtoreum ten drachms, Aſſafoetida, Opoponax, of each ſix drachms: honey ſcummed, twice the weight of all the reſt. Make them into an Electuary; The Doſe whereof is one drachm every morning.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary for the weakneſs and dimneſs of Sight.</head>
                  <p>Take of the ſeeds of Fennel one
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170251:43"/> pound and half, Mountain-Withy half a pound, Germander half an ounce, the roots of Selendine five drachms, the ſeeds of Aniſe, Smallage, Parſley, of each one ounce and half: Penyroyal, Hyſſop, Borage-flowers, Juniper-ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Saxifrage, of each one ounce and half; and with honey ſcummed, let it be made into an Electuary. This very Medicine cured a certain woman who was almoſt blinde for nine years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The Doſe of it is half an ounce in the morning.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary for an Inflammation and pain in the eyes.</head>
                  <p>Take of the waters of Roſes, Eye-bright, and Vervain, of each half an ounce: Tutty prepared one drachm, Mother of Pearl finely powdered two drachms, powder of Salendine, Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, Roſes, Vervain, Aniſeed, of each half an ounce. Make them into an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuary, with a little honey, if need require. The Doſe is one drachm.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:170251:43"/>
                  <head>For a Cough and Hoarſeneſs.</head>
                  <p>Take Diapenid. Diareos, of each one ounce: the pulp of Raiſins, and juyce of Liquorice, Hyſſop, of each half an ounce: ſyrup of Horehound as much as will ſuffice to make it up into an Electuary; of which take the quantity of a Cheſnut at a time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Lac Sulphuris rightly prepared ten grains, Balſamum Sulphuris two grains, flower of Sulphur half an ounce, Liquoriſh and Enula-campane, of each three drachms: Conſerve of old Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Lohoch Sanum, Lohoch of Foxes lungs, of each one ounce: oyl of ſweet Almonds as much as will ſuffice to make it up into an Electuary, adding thereunto ſpirit of Sulphur twenty drops; of which take the quantity of a Cheſnut every morning and night, drinking a draught of Mace-Ale af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:170251:44"/>
                  <head>An Electuary for the Dropſie.</head>
                  <p>Take a little quantity of Ginger, Salt of Wormwood one ounce: incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate it with a ſufficient quantity of the oyl of Salt, to make it up into an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary; of which take every day ſix grains.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary for a Catarrhe, or, a Rheum diſtilling from the brain to the throat and ſtomack.</head>
                  <p>Take of the oldeſt Conſerve of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes one ounce, Olibanum one drachm and half, powder of Liquoriſh one drachm, Sugar-candy one ounce, ſyrup of Hyſſop as much as will ſuffice to make it into an Electuary; of which take the quantity of a Nut often in a day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another of the ſame vertue.</head>
                  <p>Take of Lohoch ſanum, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve of Roſes, of each half an ounce; Laudanum four grains, juyce of Liquo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh three drachms, Philonum Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170251:44"/> ſix grains; and with the ſyrup of Poppies make it into an Electuary; of which take the quantity of a Nut every night going to bed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary for all ſorts of Coughs.</head>
                  <p>Take Liquoriſh, Hyſſop dry, Orris, Maidenhair, Coltsfoot, of each one ounce; Origanum three drachms, Foxes lungs prepared one ounce and half, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney ſcummed, Sugar, of each ſix ounces: reduce them into a powder, and make them into an Electuary with two oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Aqua vitae; and eat thereof when occaſion ſerves.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary to purge the ſtomack of groſs humours.</head>
                  <p>Take of Maidenhair freſh three oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the roots of Orris, Pine-kernels, Liquoriſh, Carpobalſamum, Horehound, Chamomile-flowers, round Birthwort, of each one ounce and half. Let them be finely beaten and ſifted, and with the ſyrup made of Honey and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction of Maidenhair, (boiled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to a conſiſtency) make it into an
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170251:45"/> Electuary; of which take three drach. in a draught of the decoction of Hore-hound, Liquoriſh, and Hyſſop.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary for an old Cough.</head>
                  <p>Take of the juyce of Horehound half an ounce, Liquoriſh one ounce, round Birthwort ſix drachms, flower of Sulphur two drachms, Sugar-candy half an ounce. Make it into an Electu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary with Honey.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another for a continued Cough.</head>
                  <p>Take of Aniſeed two drachms, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus two ſcruples, Myrrhe one drachm, Galbanum, white Peper, Henbane, Opium, juyce of Liquoriſh, of each one drachm and half; Saffron half a drach. ſyrup of Hyſſop as much as will ſuffice to bring it to the conſiſtencie of an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuary; part of which muſt be exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited going into bed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another of the ſame nature.</head>
                  <p>Take Diapenidii, Diatraganthi, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar of Violets, of each half an ounce:
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170251:45"/> with the ſyrup of Liquoriſh make it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Electuary. The Doſe is two drachms.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A pectoral Electuary.</head>
                  <p>Take Lohoch of Pine-kernels one ounce, Diatraganth frigid. two drach. Orris root half an ounce, Green-Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger one ounce, Liquoriſh and Enula-campane in powder, of each one drachm and half: Sugar-candy in pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der two ounces, pulp of Roſes three ounces, pulp of Raiſins one ounce, tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of Saffron, Aqua coeleſtis, of each one ſcruple; ſpirit of Vitriol fifteen drops: mix them up according to art, into an Electuary; adding, if need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, ſyrup of Jujubees to mollifie it; of which take the quantity of a Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, three times a day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary for the afflictions of the Liver and Brest.</head>
                  <p>Take of the pulp of Raiſins ſtoned four ounces, Saffron one drachm, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamus Aromaticus, Bdellium, Squi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, of each one ounce and half;
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170251:46"/> Caſſia-wood one drachm, Cynamon half a drachm, Spikenard three drach. Myrrhe two drachms, Turpentine half an ounce, Honey two ounces, the beſt Wine as much as will ſuffice to coct them up into the conſiſtency of an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuary; of which take the quantity of a Nutmeg, when occaſion ſerves.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary to hinder Abortion.</head>
                  <p>Take Conſerve of Roſes, Borage and Bugloſs, of each half an ounce; Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>margarit. frigid. four ſcruples, Pearl two drachms, the fragments of precious ſtones one drachm, red Coral two ſcruples: mingle them into an Electu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; of which eat about a quarter of an ounce when the moſt danger is.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary for the Hicket.</head>
                  <p>Take of black, white, and long Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, of each three drachms; Xylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balſamum one ounce, Spikenard, Ladies Roſe, the ſeeds of Smallage, Reſt-har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, Ginger, Lovage, Caſſia-wood, Enulacampane, the roots of Aſara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacca, of each three drachms. Let
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170251:46"/> them be made with Honey well ſcum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, into an Electuary. The Doſe hereof is one drachm, three hours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore meals, rolling and wrapping it in a wafer moiſtened with Wine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary to purge the Lungs.</head>
                  <p>Take of Turpentine prepared with the juyce of Lemmons three drachms, Honey of Roſes ſolutive three ounces: mingle them: take of this two drach. or three, twice or thrice a day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary for ulcerated Lungs.</head>
                  <p>Take of Lohoch ſanum one ounce and half, Lohoch of Foxes lungs two ounces, Lac Sulphuris one ſcruple, Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting Wine, Oyl of ſweet Almonds, of each half an ounce; flower of Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone five drachms; and with the ſyrup of Liquoriſh and Jujubees make it up into a ſoft Electuary; of which take the quantity of a Cheſnut, twice or thrice a day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:170251:47"/>
                  <head>An Electuary to purge watry humours.</head>
                  <p>Take Cremor, Tartar, Alexandrian Senna, of each one ounce and half; Manna, red Sugar, of each one ounce; Ginger, Aniſeed, Cynamon, Galanga, of each one drachm; ſyrup of Roſes five ounces: make it up into an Electuary. Of this Electuary take half an ounce: diſſolve it in three ounces of White-wine, adding thereunto ſix drachms of the ſyrup of Buckthorn-barries; which muſt be taken in the morning, keeping within doors: and ſo to dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh or increaſe the quantity of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuary, as it operates upon the body.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary for ſuch as have a cold body.</head>
                  <p>Take preſerved Orris, Conſerve of Stoechados, and Roſemary, of each three drachms, Andromachus his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, commonly called Venice-Treacle one drachm and an half, Electuarium Aromaticum Roſatum, ſpecies Diam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brae, Cloves, of each half a drachm; and with the ſyrup of preſerved ſweet
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170251:47"/> Cane make it into an Electuary: of which take a little at morning and night.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary for Barrenneſs: or, A means to cauſe Conception.</head>
                  <p>Take of preſerved Eringo, Citron-pill condited, of each one ounce; green Ginger, Conſerve of Roſemary-flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers one ounce and half, the powder of a Bulls peezle, the powder of a Hares womb, Cocks treads, of each half an ounce; ſpecies Diagalangal, Diamoſch dulc. of each two drachms; Pine-kernels, Hazle-nuts, of each three drachms; Staggs peezle two ſcruples, Lambs ſtones burnt four ſcruples, Sugar a little; and with the ſyrup of preſerved Citron, make it into an Electuary, of which often take about the quantity of a Nutmeg in a cup of Claret.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:170251:48"/>
                  <head>An Electuary for a Rupture.</head>
                  <p>Take Conſerve of old Roſes, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey, Sage-flowers, and Acorus, of each one ounce: Troches of Amber three drachms, Blatta-Byzant, (a fiſhes ſhell ſo called) burnt, and waſht in water, Cauda Equina two drachms; and with the ſyrup of Quinces make it into an Electuary. The Doſe of this is one drachm, drinking after it a little Red-wine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary againſt a Hectick Fever.</head>
                  <p>Take Conſerve of Bugloſs, Borage, Violets and Satyrion, of each one ounce; Pine-kernels infuſed in milk, the four greater cool ſeeds decortica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, Cotton-ſeed, of each two drach. Snails prepared with ſalt and White-wine one ounce, Aniſe one drachm, Cynamon one ſcruple; and with the ſyrup of Succory make it into an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary. The Doſe is two drachms.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:170251:48"/>
                  <head>An Electuary for the yellow Jaundies.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Conſerve of Maiden-hair, and the roots of Smallage, of each one ounce and half; Marigold-flowers one ounce, the powder of the three Sanders two drachms, Diarrhodon Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batis one drachm, the four greater cool ſeeds ſmall cut, of each two drachms; and with the ſyrup of Endive make it into the conſiſtence of an Electuary. The Doſe is two drachms, drinking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it one ounce of graſs-water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary againſt the winde of the Spleen.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Conſerve of Spleen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort two ounces, Troches of Capers one drachm, Diarrhodon Abbatis, Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galanga, of each one drachm and half; the filings of Steel macerated in Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and finely powdered, three drach. the ſeeds of Purſlain one drachm; and with ſyrup of Sorrel make it up into an Electuary, taking of it every day the quantity of a Cheſnut, drinking after it a little water of Tamaris.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:170251:49"/>
                  <head>An Electuary for ulcerated Reins.</head>
                  <p>Take of Caſſia newly extracted from the Cane four ounces, Tamarindarum, Mixarum, of each one ounce, mucilage of Fleabane-ſeed ſix drachms: with ſyrup of Violets make it into an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary; of which take a little, and diſſolve it in Barly-water, and ſo drink it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary for ſuch as piſs their beds.</head>
                  <p>Take Spodium torrefied, Lignum-Aloes, Purſlain-ſeed, Gum-Arabick and Thraganth, Barberries, Turbith, the ſeeds of Endive, Bole-Armeniack, of each four drachms; and with the ſyrup of Myrtles and Honey, make it up into an Electuary.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another for the ſame purpoſe.</head>
                  <p>Take of the bladders of Oxen, Sheep, Hoggs, of each twelve: dry them in an oven till they may be powdered: Harts peezle, the rib of a dead man powdered, of each two drachms; and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170251:49"/> with ſyrup of Quinces make it into an Electuary; of which take half an ounce mornings and nights, drinking after it a glaſs of Red-wine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary to procure ſleep.</head>
                  <p>Take of Roſes, Violets, of each one drachm and half; Opium, Henbane, white Poppie, the bark of the root of Mandrake, the ſeeds of Endive, Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, Purſlain, Fleabane, Nutmeg, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, Sugar, of each one drachm and half; the three Sanders, burnt Ivory, Thraganth, of each one ſcruple; Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y deſpumed a treble quantity. Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle them, and make them into an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary; of which take half a drachm at night going to bed, or one ſcruple, or leſs, according to the conſtitution of the perſon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Electuary for the vices of the Ventricle, Liver and Spleen.</head>
                  <p>Take Troches of Wormwood, Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Roſes, the roots of Gentian, the flowers of the leſſer Centory, of each half a drachm; Diarrhodon Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batis,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170251:50"/> the roots of Comfrey, Marſh-Mallows, Liquoriſh, of each four ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; Pimpinel, Amber, of each one drachm and half; Red Coral, Lemnian earth, Pearl, Bezoar, Cryſtal, of each one ſcruple; Maſtich two drachms, Steel brought into powder without Vinegar half an ounce: Conſerve of Maidenhair one ounce, Extract of Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Cherries ſix drachms, Conſerve of the Flowers of Angelico two ounces, ſhavings of Harts-horn extracted with Wine one ounce, Extract of Saffron ten grains, fine Sugar one pound and half: with the decoction of the roots of Marſh-Mallows, let it be made into an Electuary; adding Roſe-water two ounces, ſpirit of Sulphur one drachm: mingle them. Take of this the quantity of a Nutmeg, when occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion calls for it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A cordial Electuary for all commotions of the minde.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Extract of Saffron two ſcruples, Diambrae one drachm. Let them be moiſtened with oyl of Cyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon as much as will ſuffice: then take
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170251:50"/> Setwel and Angelico of each half a drachm. Let theſe be ſprinkled and madefied with the Oyl of Aniſeed, Venice-Treacle two drachms, Musk eight grains, Philonium Romanum half a drachm: mingle them. Of this take a little upon a knife-point, when occaſion calls for it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>EMPLASTRA:</hi> OR, Emplaiſters.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Plaiſter for the Pleureſie.</head>
                  <p>TAke of the roots of Marſh-Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows four handfuls, flower of Barley four ounces, Chamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile-flowers one ounce, Melilot-flowers, Violets, of each halfe an ounce; oyl of Chamomile, Almonds, of each two ounces: make thereof a Plaiſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:170251:51"/>
                  <head>Another for the ſame nature.</head>
                  <p>Take of the roots of Lilies and Marſh-Mallows, of each two ounces; Mallows, Pellitory, Violets, of each one handful; flowers of Melilot, Chamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile, Elder, of each one pugil; Linſeed, Fenugreek, of each one drachm; boyle them, but firſt let them be bruiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according to Art, and then pour off the Liquor, and in a ſtone-morter beat the things boyled: to which add, Oyl of Chamomile, ſweet Almonds, Capons-greaſe, of each one ounce; beane-flour, as much as will ſuffice to body it: apply it over the whole ſide where the Pleuriſie is; but before it be applyed, let the ſide be anointed with Sperma Ceti, and Oyl of Almonds.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Plaiſter for the Quinſy.</head>
                  <p>Take of the juice of Briony, hony, of each three ounces; the flower of Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed, Fenugreek, and Wheat, of each half an ounce; freſh-Butter two ounces, Saffron half a drachm: mingle them, and make thereof a plaiſter: apply it hot about the Neck.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:170251:51"/>
                  <head>A Plaiſter for the ſtomach.</head>
                  <p>Take oyl of Wormwood, Minte, Red-roſes, Maſtich, of each halfe an ounce; oyl of Spike, Nutmegs, of each to drachms; the powder of Mace, Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs, Cloves, of each one ſcruple; Wax waſhed in Aqua vitae one ounce: make thereof a plaiſter; which apply to the ſtomach, eſpecially if the affection doth proceed from cold humors.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Plaiſter to corroborate the Ventricle.</head>
                  <p>Take Taccamahac halfe an ounce, Storax one ounce and halfe, oyntment of Orange-flowers two drachms, oyl of Mace one drachm, oyl of Cinamon ſix dropps, Amber-greaſe ſix grains; mingle them, and let them be made into a plaiſter, and applyed to the Ventricle.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Emplaſtrum ſtomach. ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſteriale one ounce, Caranna, Maſtich, Storax ſtained, of each to drachms: Balſamum of Peru, one drachm and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170251:52"/> halfe, oyl of Cinamon one ſcruple: ſpread it upon Leather, and let a Sarſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net overſpread the plaiſter, and ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it to the ſtomach.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Plaiſter to ſtop the flux of a Catarrhe.</head>
                  <p>Take Roſine one ounce, Laudanum two drachms, Citron-pill, Lignum-A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loes, of each two ſcruples: ſpicknard one ſcruple, Cloves half a ſcruple: the gums muſt be diſſolved in Vinegar; let the plaiſter be in breadth four fingers, and in length five; which muſt be applyed upon the Crown of the head, the haire being ſhaven off.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Plaiſter to ſtay Vomiting.</head>
                  <p>Take Wormwood, Minte, of each one handful; a dryed cruſt of bread, infuſed in Vinegar, half a pound, Maſtick half an ounce, Cloves, Mace, of each two drachms: let thoſe be powdered that are to be beaten, and all commixed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in a morter with oyl of quinces, into the form of a plaiſter; which muſt be applyed to the ſtomach.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:170251:52"/>
                  <head>A Plaiſter for the paine of the Spleen.</head>
                  <p>Take Amoniacum, Bdellium, of each one ounce: diſſolve them in Vinegar of Squills, and ſo boyl them a little: af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards add of the beſt Agarick pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, the bark of the roots of Capers one drachm; black Hellebor half a drachm Goats dung two drachms, Wax as much as will ſuffice to body it into an Emplaiſter, and ſo to apply it ſpread upon Leather to the place affected.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Plaiſter againſt Worms.</head>
                  <p>Take of the beſt Treacle half an ounce; Myrrhe, Aloes, Dittany, Genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, Wormwood, Tormentil, of each half a drachm: make them into a powder, and with a heifers gall and Vinegar brought into a plaiſter: which apply to the ſtomach and navel.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another of the ſame vertue.</head>
                  <p>Take Gentian, Wormwood, Savine, Sow bread, of each one drachm; Aloes, two drachms; Theriaca, Diateſſeron, three ſcruples and an half; juice of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170251:53"/> Woorwood, and Vinegar of Squills, as much as will ſuffice to incorporate the powders, which muſt be applyed as before.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Plaiſter for ſuch as piſs in their beds.</head>
                  <p>Take Laudanum, Maſtich, of each two drachms; Aloes-wood, Cypreſs-Nuts, Storax, Cinamon, Turpentine, of each one drach. Olibanum half a drach. mingle them, and with the juyce of Mints, incorporate them into a plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, which apply to the Pecten and Perinaeum.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Plaiſter to prevent the coming down of the Matrix.</head>
                  <p>Take Maſtich, Laudanum, of each three drachms; Galbanum half an ounce, Gum-ſtorax two drachms; make hereof a plaiſter, which apply to the belly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another for the ſame purpoſe.</head>
                  <p>Take Emplaſtrum pro Matrice half an ounce, Storax and Galbanum, of each
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170251:53"/> three drachms; Liquid Storax, one drachm. Melt theſe together, and ſpread them upon a peece of Leather, in the middle fixing a little Cotton-wool, wherein wrap four graines of the beſt Civet, which place juſt upon the Navel.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Plaiſter to hinder Abortion.</head>
                  <p>Take Maſtich half an ounce, Lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num three drachms, Yellow-wax two drachms, Biſtort, Cypreſs-Nuts, Mirabolans, the juice of Ciſtus, Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, ſealed Earth, Red-roſes, Bole-Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meniack, of each one drachm and half: mingle them, and make thereof a maſs, which may be ſpread upon a piece of Parchment, and applyed to the Navel.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Plaiſter to be uſed when abortion is fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from a cold cauſe.</head>
                  <p>Take Maſtich five drachms, Clarifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed roſine, ſhip-pitch, Storax, Yellow-wax, of each one drachm and half; Laudanum three drachms; Mint, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtort, Frankincenſe, Gallia Moſchata, Galbanum, Myrrhe, Gum-Arabick,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170251:54"/> meg, of each one drachm and half; and with Turpentine, make it into a plaiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, which muſt be applyed to the groyne, and reines.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Plaiſter to Corrode fleſh.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Egyptian Unguent two drachms; oyl of Mirtles one ounce; Mirtle-berryes, Olibanum, of each one drachm: Red Wax as much as will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to make it into a Plaiſter, to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied where neceſſity calls for it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Plaiſter for the Tooth-ach.</head>
                  <p>Take Spaniſh Flyes one ſcruple, Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorbeum four grains: mix them with about a drachm of Coblers wax, and ſo ſpread it upon a little piece of Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and apply it under the ear; which in twelve hours time will raiſe a bli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: then remove it, and let the humour out, clapping another plaiſter, made of Melilot, to the place: the like may be done in Cararrhs, applying the ſame Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiccatory, to the fore part of the head, which will divert the Rheum from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:170251:54"/>
                  <head>A Plaiſter againſt the pain of the Gout.</head>
                  <p>Take juyce of Poppy, Wormwood, Houſe-leeke, of each three drachms; Dialtheae one ounce: Bullocks-dung freſh, one ounce; two yolks of Eggs, Biſcat three drachms; Saffron one ſcruple: the leaves of Violets, Mercury, Purſlain, water-lilyes: let theſe be bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and with one ounce of oyl of Roſes, made into a plaiſter, and apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed where the pain is.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A diſcuſſing Plaiſter.</head>
                  <p>Take Bdellium, Amoniacum, of each two drachms; Turpentine half an ounce: Hyſſop, Rue, Chamomile, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and ſifted, oyl of Bayes one ounce, of the beſt Treacle two drachms, Saffron one ſcruple and half, oyl of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momile one ounce, Wax as much as will ſuffice to incorporate it into a plaiſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Plaiſter to ſtay the Whites.</head>
                  <p>Take white and red Coral, of each
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170251:55"/> one drachm and half; Amber one ſcruple, Roſes, Plantain-ſeed, of each one drachm; the flakes of Iron pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared ſix drachms, Galbanum half an ounce, Vinegar as much as ſuffices for the Conſiſtency of a plaiſter: which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to the Belly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another of the ſame Nature.</head>
                  <p>Take bread toaſted, and well infuſed in the juyce of Mint and Vinegar one ounce, Maſtich, Balanſtians, Bole-Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meniack, of each one drachm; mingle them into a plaiſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Plaiſter for the Dropſy.</head>
                  <p>Take of the roots of Cucumbers, and Dwarf-Elder, of each two ounces; the flour of Barly ten ounces, Goats-dung dry one pound, Vinegar one ounce and half; Orris-root three drachms: make thereof of a plaiſter, with our Hydroptical Lixinium.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another for the Dropſy.</head>
                  <p>Take Boars-greaſe one pound, oyl
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170251:55"/> of Dill, Chamomile, Bayes, of each one ounce: the roots and leaves of Dwarf-Elder, Marſh-Mallows, of each half a pound: Orris four ounces, the juyce of Smallage and Parſly, of each one ounce: the ſeeds of Smallage and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly, of each half an ounce: Cloves two drachms; white wine ſix ounces, Childrens piſs four ounces, Turpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine four ounces, wax three ounces: mingle them, and boyl them according to art, till the juyce and the wine be conſumed, and then make thereof a plaiſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Plaiſter for ſuch as are troubled with ſwoundings.</head>
                  <p>Take of the oyls of Dill and Chamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile, of each one ounce and half: Aloes-wood, Citron-pill, Nutmeg, Cinamon, Galanga, of each one ſcruple; all the Sanders, red-Roſes, of each half a ſcruple; Gallia Moſchata three grains, Wax as much as will ſuffice to make it into a plaiſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:170251:56"/>
                  <head>A Plaiſter for a certain blackneſs in the Face, proceeding from a blow or contuſion.</head>
                  <p>Take of the roots of the greater Comfrey, and the leſſer, of each half a pound; the flowers of Chamomile, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilot, of each two drachms; Saffron half a drachm; Bean-flour four ounces: the flower of Fenugreek one ounce and half; Butter five ounces, Wormwood, Cummin, of each one ounce: after that the roots are boyled, beat them with the reſt into the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtency of a plaiſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Plaiſter to take away Corns.</head>
                  <p>Take Galbanum, Amoniacum, of each equal parts: diſſolve them in Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar of Squills, boyling them to a juſt Conſiſtency, adding oyl Vitriol a few drops: then ſpread it upon Leather, and apply it to the place.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Plaiſter for the pain of the Head.</head>
                  <p>Take Caranna, Taccamahaca, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtich,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170251:56"/> of each one drachm; diſſolve them in a pipkin, adding thereto oyl of Nutmegs one ſcruple: ſpread it upon Sarſnet, and apply it to the forehead.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>EPITHEMATA:</hi> OR Epithemes.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Epitheme to corroborate ſtrength.</head>
                  <p>TAke of the water of Balm, Scabious, and Carduus, of each three ounces: White-wine one ounce, Confection of Alkermes, and de Hyacintho, of each four ſcruples: Troches of Burnt-Ivory, Kermes ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Citron-ſeed, of each one ſcruple: Diambrae, Diamoſch dulc. of each half a drachm: Saffron five grains. Mingle them, and let them be made into an Epithema; with which foment the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the heart, warm, twice or thrice in a day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:170251:57"/>
                  <head>Another of the ſame nature.</head>
                  <p>Take of the waters of Roſes, Sorrel, Bugloſs, of each three ounces: all the Sanders, both the Corals, of each one ounce and half; Camphyr three grains, Diamargarit. frig. one drachm; Saffron one ſcruple, Vinegar a little, make thereof an Epithema, fomenting the heart therewith morning and night.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Epithema for the affections of the heart.</head>
                  <p>Take of the waters of Borage, Bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſs, Roſes, of each three ounces: Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligo wine one ounce, powder of Gems one drachm, the juyce of Citron half an ounce, Troches of Camphor one ſcruple, Chriſtal one drachm; mingle them, and make thereof an Epithema, which ſprinkle upon a piece of Scarlet, and clap warm to the heart, renewing it often.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Epitheme to be uſed in hot burning Feavers.</head>
                  <p>Take of Barly cleanſed half a Pugil, the flowers of Violets two Pugils, the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170251:57"/> four greater Coole-ſeeds two ounces: water-Lillyes one pugil: boyl them in water, ſtrain out three pints: diſſolve therein oyl of ſweet Almonds and Violets, of each three ounces: let them be ſtirred together with a wooden Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tula, and make thereof an Epithema, which apply upon the whole Thorax.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Epitheme for the Liver in hot fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</head>
                  <p>Take of the waters of Endive and Succory of each three ounces: Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood water one ounce and half; white wine Vinegar one ounce, the ſeeds of Sorrel and Purſlain of each half an ounce: the powder of all the Sanders of each a drachm mingle them, and make thereof an Epitheme, with which fove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>are the region of the Liver.
<q>But the heart muſt firſt be corroborated with an Epitheme, leſt the putrid vapors be tranſmitted from the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our parts to the vitalls.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Epitheme for the Hemorrhoids.</head>
                  <p>Take of the waters of Roſes, Sorrel,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170251:58"/> Plantain and Bugloſs of each three ounces: all the three Sanders, both the Corrals of each one drachm and half; Troches of Camphor one drach. the ſeeds of Purſlain half a drachm; the ſeeds of Poppy one ſcruple, Vinegar a little: make of this mixture an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theme, with which foveate the Hemor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhoid veines branching out at the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dament.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>ERRHINA:</hi> OR Errhines.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Errhine for Choler.</head>
                  <p>TAke of the juyce of Roſes, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dive and Lettice of each one ounce, decoction of Barly and Melon-ſeed three ounces; mingle them, and diſſolve therein ſyrup of Roſes ſolutive one ounce.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:170251:58"/>
                  <head>Or thus.</head>
                  <p>Take of the decoction of Barly one pound, Hony of Roſes two ounces, juyce of plantain and Nightſhade, of each one ounce: Pomgranate-wine one ounce and half: make thereof an Errhine, which is to be ſquirted up the Noſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Errhine for flegm.</head>
                  <p>Take Roſe-water half a pint, the juyce of Marjoran Clarifyed four ounces, juyce of Betony two ounces, juyce of Roſemary one ounce, Gallia Moſchata one ſcruple: let this be often drawn up at the Noſtrills.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A ſtronger for the ſame purpoſe.</head>
                  <p>Take of the roots of Sowbread one drachm, Elaterium half a drachm: let them be beaten into fine powder, and macerated in four ounces of white-wine; ſtrain out the Liquor, and let this Liquor by little and little be drawn up into the Noſtrils.
<q>But it doth not behove every one to meddle with this Medicine, except thoſe whoſe knowledg can inform them how to order it.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:170251:59"/>
                  <head>An Errhine for the ulcers of the Noſtrills.</head>
                  <p>Take of the tops of Mirtles one handful, two unripe quinces cut into peeces; boyl them with water and wine: if there be an Inflammation, let them be boyled onely in Vinegar, and then make a ſtrong Expreſſion: add to the Colature Hony of Roſes four ounces, and make thereof an Errhine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Errhine for the Yellow Jaundiſe.</head>
                  <p>Take of the juyce of Roſes two ounces, juyce of Betony one ounce, Scammony one drachm, Hony of Roſes three ounces: boyl them to a good Conſiſtency, and ſo put it up into the Noſtrills with your finger.
<q>Thoſe who labor under any diſtemper of the eyes, the uſe of theſe Errhines are very Noxious to them, and alſo to ſuch as are troubled with the Vertigo, and Epileptick fits; becauſe they make a Commotion in the brain, and excite the humours which occaſion the Fits.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:170251:59"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>FOMENTATIONES.</hi> OR, Fomentations.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Fomentation for the coming down of the Womb.</head>
                  <p>TAke Chamomile, Sage, Balanſtians, Galls, the bark of Oak, Knot-graſs, and Pine-leaves, of each one handful and half; Medlars one handful: boyl them in Chalibeate water: adde to the Colature Dragons blood, B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le-Armeniack, Troches of Sealed earth, of each one drachm. After that they are well boyled, foment the womb therewith.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A fomentation gently inciting to ſleep.</head>
                  <p>Take oyl of Roſes one drachm; Roſe-water, Vinegar, womans Milk, of each half an ounce: Nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>megs two drachms, Poppy water half an ounce:
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170251:60"/> mingle them, and foment the front therewith very warm.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A fomentation to the gravel in the reines.</head>
                  <p>Take of Marſh-Mallows, with the roots Mallows, Pellitory, Mercury, (the herb) Chamomile-flowers, and Melilor, of each one handful; Linſeed, and Fenugreek, of each four ounces: and to the Colature add oyl of Chamomile, and bitter Almonds, of each two ounces: and ſo with a Spunge foment the region of the reines, as hot as it can be endured.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A fomentation againſt the windy ſwelling of the womb.</head>
                  <p>Take of Mugwort, Hyſſop, Betony, Calamint, Peniroyal, tops of Bayes, Juniper-berries, of each one handful; the ſeeds of Fennel, Annis and Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, of each two drachms: boyl them in ſmall wine, and foment the lower part of the belly therewith.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:170251:60"/>
                  <head>A fomentation for the redueſs of the Face.</head>
                  <p>Take Mercury ſublimed and finely powdered half a drachm; let it be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed in juyce of Lemmons, five or ſix hours; bitter Almonds blanched, and beaten to a paſte four ounces: water two pints, Camphyr one ſcruple: mingle them, and make thereof a fomentation, with which foment the Face, with a fine Spunge, morning and night: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of the eyes and mouth, leſt any of the Liquor enter in there.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A fomentation for a Cough.</head>
                  <p>Take Sage, ſweet Marjoran, Betony, Balme, Staechados, Chamomile, of each equal parts: boyl them in a ſufficient quantity of water, with which whilſt it is hot, foment the Thighs and Legs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A fomentation for ſuch as have puſtulls or ſcabbs in their Faces, ariſing from a venereal cauſe.</head>
                  <p>Take of the beſt prepared Praeci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:170251:61"/> twelve grains: inject it into ſix ounces of Plantain water; boyl it till it comes to three: foment the ſpots with the water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A ſtronger for the ſame purpoſe.</head>
                  <p>Take of Mercury two darchms, Plantain water, and Hony-ſuckle-water of each four ounces: infuſe them for four hours, and with the clear water foment the ſpots.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A fomentation for a Pleuriſy.</head>
                  <p>Take of Chamomile three handfuls, Wormwood two handfuls, Bay-leaves one handful, the flowers of Chamomile and Melilot, of each three pugils; Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed and Fenugreek, of each half an ounce: boyl theſe in a ſufficient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of water, till it comes to four pints: ſtrain it, and put the Colature in Ox-bladders, applying it as hot as can be endured to the ſide laboring under the Pleuriſy.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:170251:61"/>
                  <head>Another for a Pleuriſy.</head>
                  <p>Take the roots of Marſh-Mallows and Lillyes, of each two ounces; Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed and Fenugreek, of each three ounces: Chamomile, Dill, and Bayes, of each one handful; the flowers of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilot and Elder, of each one pugil. Boyl them in a ſufficient quantity of water, and with a Spunge whilſt it is hot fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the ſide, afterwards clapping to this Cataplaſm. Capons-greaſe, oyl of Almonds, and ol. Irrinum, of each e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual parts; Bay-berries three ounces finely powdered: make thereof a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taplaſm, applying it as warm as it can be ſuffered.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A fomentation for the Scurvy.</head>
                  <p>Take of Wormwood three handfulls, S. Johns-wort, Germander, Ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine, Chamomile, of each two hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulls: Scurvy-graſs, Brooklime, water-Creſſes, Elder, of each four handfulls; Sage two handfulls, horſe reddiſh root four ounces; boyl them in a ſuffi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt quantity of water for a fomentation,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170251:62"/> with which foment the parts for the ſpace of two hours twice a day: and after that the fomentation hath been uſed, let the parts be anointed with an Unguent for the ſame purpoſe, deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in its proper place.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>GARGARISMATA:</hi> OR, Gargariſmes.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Gargariſme mitigating pain.</head>
                  <p>TTake Mouſe-eare, Chamomile, Melilot, Dill, of each half a handful; red-Roſes one pugil, Raiſins ſtoned one ounce: ſix ſound figs: boyl them in wine and water, of each e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual parts, till it comes to two pints: add thereunto of the muſilidge of Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed and Fenugreek of each three ounces: make thereof a Gargariſm, and with a ſyringe ſquirt it into the mouth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:170251:62"/>
                  <head>A Gargariſm to be uſed in a hot Catarrhe.</head>
                  <p>Take of the roots of Cinqfoil two ounces: Cypreſs-roots, Cypreſs-Nuts, Knotgraſs, Pomegranate-pill, of each half an ounce; boyl them in water and Vinegar, and make thereof a Garga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm, by adding two drachms of ſyrup of Poppy.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Gargariſm in a cold Catarrhe.</head>
                  <p>Take of Ginger, Pellitory of Spain, long-Peper, Cloves, of each one drach. boyl them in a ſufficient quantity of water, till half of it be conſumed: ſtrain the reſt, and uſe it as before.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Gargariſm againſt a Quinſy.</head>
                  <p>Take of the waters of Lettice, Night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhade, Plantain, Roſes, of each four ounces; Vinegar of Roſes half an ounce: Album Graecum one drachm; ſyrup of Mulberries four ounces: Rheniſh-wine four ounces: mingle them, and uſe it with a Syringe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:170251:63"/>
                  <head>A Gargariſme for a Quinſy in its greateſt vigour.</head>
                  <p>Take ſpecies Diahirundinis, ſyrup of Mulberies, hony of Roſes, of each one ounce and half: Sugar two ounces, Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron one ſcruple, juyce of Lemmons half an ounce, Succory water half a pint, Plantain water two ounces: mingle them, and with a Syringe often waſh the mouth, leaning backwards, Ejecting out what the Syringe puts in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Or thus.</head>
                  <p>Take Rayſons, Barly, Roſes, of each half a handful; Liquoriſh one ounce, Marſh-Mallows roots three ounces; Jujubees ten, figs five, the neaſts of Swallows half a pound: boyl theſe in the water of Roſes, Plantain, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dive; in the Colature diſſolve Diahi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rundinis one ounce, hony of Roſes three ounces, ſyrup of the fine opening roots one ounce and half; mingle them, and make thereof a Gargariſm.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:170251:63"/>
                  <head>A Gargariſm to be uſed by ſuch as labour under the ſmall Pox.</head>
                  <p>Take Jews-eares two drachms, Lentiſcks decorticated half an ounce, Liquoriſh ſix drachms, harts-horn three drachms, the inward bark of Elm two drachms, red-Roſes two pugills: boyl them in fountain water, as much as will ſuffice to make when it is ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one pinte; to which add ſyrup of Mulberries two ounces: make thereof a Gargariſm.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another for the ſame purpoſe.</head>
                  <p>Take Lentiſcks decorticated (which is a kind of vetch) one ounce; Barly, Gumlacc. Thraganth, of each one drachm; four ſound figs, eight Juju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bees, Rayſons half an ounce: boyl them in equal parts of Carduus water, and Scordium, to a pinte and half: add thereunto hony of Roſes three ounces: Conquaſs them together for a Garga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:170251:64"/>
                  <head>Or thus.</head>
                  <p>Take Jews-Ears three dragms, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoriſh ſix dragms, decocted Barley two dragms, Red-Roſe-Leaves two pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gils, Brier-tops one handful, Honey one ounce: boyl theſe in Plantain-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and take of the Colature one pound and a halfe: to which add, Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupe of Mulberries and Quinces, of each one ounce and a half: and ſo make thereof a Gargariſm, with which gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle the mouth often in a day with a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Gargariſm to be uſed by ſuch as la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour under a Feaver.</head>
                  <p>Take Briar-tops, Wood-ſorrel, Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let-leaves, of each one handful; Jews Ears two dragms: boyl them in Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain-water a ſufficient quantity, till there remains half a pint: to which add Syrup of Mulberries, and Vinegar of Roſes, of each one ounce: mingle them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:170251:64"/>
                  <head>A Gargariſm for the Relaxation of the Palate of the Mouth.</head>
                  <p>Take Balanſtians, Galls, of each half a dragm; Gum Thraganth, Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kincenſe, Maſtick, of each one dragm; Honey of Roſes two ounces, Mulber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries one ounce, Vinegar ſix dragms, Plantain-water as much as will ſuffice: make thereof a Gargariſm.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Gargariſm for the Epilepſie.</head>
                  <p>Take Hyſſop, Sage, the flowers of Roſemary, Calamint, Staechados, of each one handful; of the Roots and Seeds of Piony, of each two dragms; Pelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory one ounce: boyl them in Piony-water, and make thereof a Gargariſm.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:170251:65"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INCESSIONES:</hi> OR, Inceſsions; or a Bath.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Inceſſion againſt the Stone.</head>
                  <p>TAke Philipendula, Saxafrage, Mallows, Marſh-mallows, Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litory, of each two handfuls; the Roots of Marſh-mallows and white Lillies, of each two ounces; the flowers of Chammomile two pugils; the Seeds of Lin, Fenugreek, and Smal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidge, of each as much as ſuffices: boyl them in a large quantity of Water, till a third part of it be conſumed, and ſo uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Inceſſion for the Cholick, and to bring down the Flowers.</head>
                  <p>Take Mugwort, Sage, Betony, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamint, Origanum, Peniroyal, Hyſop, Chammomile, Melilot, Saint Johns
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170251:65"/> wort, and Southern-wood, of each half a handful; Bayes, Dittany, Rue, Savine, Marjorane, Birthwort, Aſara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacca, Ladies Roſe, Squinant, Coſtus, Balm, Roſemary, of each half a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; the Seeds of Fennel, Annis, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raway, and Cummin, of each half an ounce: boyl them in water till a third part be conſumed: let the party ſit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the reſt, whilſt hot, that the fume may aſcend up into the body.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Inceſſion against all manner of Flixes by the Fundament.</head>
                  <p>Take of Plantain, Shepherds purſe, Cyperus, Purſlain, Knotgraſs, Sumach, Mint, Mirtle-leaves, Cinkfoil, Night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhade, Water-Lillies, of each one handful; Balanſtians, Mirtle-berries, Juice of Ciſtus, of each three ounces: boyl them in Water and Red-wine, of each equal parts; and ſo uſe the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Inceſſion for the Gout.</head>
                  <p>Take of Betony, Sage, the flowers of Chamomile, Staechados, Origanum,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170251:66"/> Peniroyal, Saint Johns wort, German<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Roſemary, Bays, Acorus, Marſh-Mallows, Winter-ſavory, Fenugreek, of each two handfuls; Juniper-ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and Bay-berries, of each half an ounce: boyl them in Water till a third part be conſumed, uſe the reſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>JULAPIA.</hi> OR, Juleps.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Julep for a hot Feaver.</head>
                  <p>TAke of red-Roſes dry one ounce, Roſe-water ſcalding hot four pints: add the Flowers to the Water: which let ſtand together four or five hours, till the Liquor hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived out all the Tincture from the Roſes: add thereunto Oyl of Vitriol two dragms, which filter, adding white Sugar one pound: mingle them, and make thereof a Julep: of which take
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170251:66"/> three ſpoonfuls every two hours.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another Julep for a hot Feaver.</head>
                  <p>Take Lapis Prunella ſix dragms, Roſe-water half a pint, Sugar-candy two ounces: make thereof a Julep; adding Oyl of Cynamon three drops: of this take two ſpoonfuls every third hour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another of the ſame Nature.</head>
                  <p>Take of the ſecond decoction of Barley one pint, the beſt Sugar four ounces, Vinegar and white-Wine, of each two ounces: boyl them a very little; and in the end, add Roſe-water five ſpoonfuls: of this take a draught at a time, drinking no other drink.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Or thus.</head>
                  <p>Take of Roſe-water half a pint, Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupe of Violets, four ounces; Diatrion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantalon one dragm and a half, Oyl of Vitriol one ſcruple and a half: mingle them for a Julep: of this take four ſpoonfuls once in three hours.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:170251:67"/>
                  <head>Another Julep for a burning Feaver.</head>
                  <p>Take of Sorrel, Woodſorrel, Violets, of each one handful; Harts horn half an ounce, Scorzonery-roots two ounces, the Juice of one Lemmon: boyl theſe in three pints of Barley-water, till it comes to a quart: ſtrain it; and add to the Colature Aqua Saxoniae four ounces, Citron-water ſix ounces, Syrupe of Lemmons, and Citron, of each two ounces; Spirit of Vitriol twenty drops: of this drink three ounces once in two hours.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Julep for the Dropſie.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Syrupe of the five open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Roots three ounces, Syrupus E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buli according to our deſcription, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimony, of each two ounces; Syrupe of Hyſſop, and Horehound, of Endive compound, Maiden-hair, Byzantinus, of each one ounce and a half; Juice of Elder two ounces, Juice of Orris ſix ounces; the water of Dodder, Egri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and Endive, of each one ounce: let them be clarified and aromatized
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170251:67"/> with Diarrhodon Abatis two ſcruples; yellow Saunders, Cinamon, of each one dragm; Diamoſch dulcis half a ſcruple: make them into a Julep: the doſe thereof is half an ounce.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Julep for ſpitting of Blood.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Syrupe of Mirtles, Pop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, Purſlain, Quinces, of each one ounce and a half; Syrupe of dried Roſes two ounces; Bole Armeniack two dragms, Lapis Hematitis one dragm; the water of Purſlain, Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and Shepherds-purſe, of each two ounces and a half; Barley-water three ounces: let theſe be clarified and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romatized with yellow Saunders, and Cinamon, of each half a dragm; and make thereof a Julep, of which take two ſpoonfuls every hour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Julep for ſuch as labour under a Pleuriſy.</head>
                  <p>Take ſyrup of Hore-hound, Maiden-haire, Violets, Liqueriſh, Jujubees, of each one ounce: Scabious water three ounces; the decoction of Barley,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170251:68"/> Maiden-hair and Prunes ſix ounces, Roſe-water two drachms; make there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a Julep, adding eight drops of ſpirit of Sulphur: take a ſpoonful at a time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another for the ſame purpoſe.</head>
                  <p>Take of the juyce of ſtone-Horſe-dung ſix ounces, ſyrup of Poppies, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jubees of each two ounces; Olibanum two ſcruples; which diſſolv in one ounc. and half of white-wine; Nutmeg in powder one ſcruple and half: mix them together for a Julep: divide it into two parts, the one drink at night going to bed, the other the night following.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another for the ſame purpoſe.</head>
                  <p>Take of the waters of Trifoyl, Scabious, Goats-beard, of each two ounces; juyce of Horſe-dung one ounce, ſyrups of Liquoriſh, Maiden-haire, and Coltsfoot, of each one ounce; Boars-tooth in powder one ſcruple: mix them together, taking of this two ſpoonefulls, or three, every ſecond hour, drinking for ordinary drink a draught of Barly-water, in which boyl ſome Liquoriſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:170251:68"/>
                  <head>A pectoral Julep.</head>
                  <p>Take ſyrup of Horehound, Coltsfoot, Maiden-haire, Liquoriſh, of each one ounce; the waters of Sage, Carduus, Scabious, Hore-hound, Burnet, of each two ounces: ſpecies Diaireos one drachm and half; of the beſt Treacle one drachm, oyl of Cinamon ſix drops: mingle them, of which take a ſpoone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful or two, every two hours.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Julep for the Epilepſy.</head>
                  <p>Take of Staechados, Betony (the Conſerves of them) and of the flowers of Sage, of each one ounce: ſyrup of ſweet Cane condited, two ounces; the waters of Sage and Betony, of each ſix ounces: Aromaticum Roſatum one drachm; Conſerve of Pyony two drachms; make it into a Julep, of which take three or four ſpoonfulls before the fits.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Julep for the Hypochondriack Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly.</head>
                  <p>Take ſyrupus de pomis Redolentibus
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170251:69"/> of Fumatory, Epithimus, of each one ounce: of the waters of Bugloſs, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, Balm, Scabious of each two ounces; Pearle prepared one drachm; mingle them, and make thereof a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lep, of which take one ounce at a time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Cordial Julep.</head>
                  <p>Take ſyrup of Cloves, Gilliflowers one ounce, Cardiacae half an ounce, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of Alkermes half a drachm; Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron-water two ounces, Roſe-water half an ounce, Aqua-Mariae three ounces: mingle them: take of this one ſpooneful at a time.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:170251:69"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LINIMENTA:</hi> OR Liniments.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Liniment for ſuch as labour under a Dropſy.</head>
                  <p>TAke of Hogs-greaſe one pound, oyls of Dill, Chamomile, and Bays, of each four ounces: the roots and leaves of Dwarf-Elder, the roots and leaves of Marſh-Mallows, of each half a pound; Orris three ounces, juyce of Smallidge, and Parſly, of each half an ounce; Cloves two drachms; white-wine ſix ounces, Childrens urine three ounces; Turpentine, Wax, of each four ounces: mingle them, and boyl them till the wine and the juyce be Conſumed; then ſtrain them, and make thereof a Liniment, with which anoint the parts affected.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:170251:70"/>
                  <head>A Liniment for the Scorbutical and Droptical humors.</head>
                  <p>Take of Garden-Scurvygraſs ſix hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulls, ſalt Scurvygraſs and water-Creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of each four handfulls, Chamomile and Brooklime of each two handfulls, Lavender and Horſeradiſh-root of each one handful and half: boyl theſe in Neates-foot-oyl three pound, (but firſt juyce one half of them, the other boyl) till the juyce be conſumed; preſs out the oyl, and with this oyl anoint the parts daily.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Liniment for the Palſy.</head>
                  <p>Take of Common oyl two pound, Chamomile flowers one handful and half; Sage, Betony, Roſemary, of each one handful, Caſtoreum half an ounce: Euphorbeum two drachms; Myrrhe, Bdellium, gum of Ivy, of each two drachms; white Poppy, Muſtard-ſeed, of each one drachm; Caſtor-wine one pound: let thoſe be powdered, that are to be beaten groſſely; boyl them with Cinamon, Maſtich, Enula-campane
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170251:70"/> and Acorus, of each one drachm, to the Conſumption of the wine: after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards let it be ſtrained, and add oyl of Turpentine three drachms; and make thereof a Liniment, with which anoint the parts.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Liniment for the palpitation or panting of the heart.</head>
                  <p>Take oyl of Dill, Mace, of each one ounce: Aloes-wood, Citron-pill, Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, Cinamon, Galanga, of each one ſcruple and half; all the three Sanders, red-Roſes, of each half a ſcruple; Gallia Moſchata ſix graines: Wax a little, to body it into a Liniment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Liniment to cauſe ſleep.</head>
                  <p>Take Uuguentum Refrigerans, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puleon, juyce of Henbane, Letice, oyl of Roſes, Violets, of each half an ounce; Opium one ſcruple and half, diſſolved in wine: make thereof a Liniment, with which anoint the Temples.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:170251:71"/>
                  <head>A Linament for the pain of the Gout.</head>
                  <p>Take Oyl of Roſes half a pound, white-Wax ſix ounces, Turpentine three ounces, Gum Elemni two ounces, Alume three dragms, freſh-Butter ſix dragms; Vinegar, white-Wine, the Waters of Roſes, Lettice, and Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, of each two ounces; Juice of Purſlain, Knotgraſs, of each one ounce: boyl them together for eight hours, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards preſs it out into a clean Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel: and when it is almoſt cold, then add Fenugreek one dragm, the three Saunders of each one dragm and a half; Bole-Armeniack, Dragons Blood, of each two dragms; ſealed Earth one dragm, Ceruſe three dragms, Lithargy of Gold and Silver, of each two dragms; Red Coral three dragms, Muſilidge of Marſh-mallow-roots one ounce: let thoſe that are to be beaten, be finely powdered, and all mingled, ſtirring of them with a Spatula, till it be cold.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="275" facs="tcp:170251:71"/>
                  <head>A Liniment for the Cramp.</head>
                  <p>Take oyl of Earth-Worms, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of a Bullocks Neck, the Suet of a Ram, Caſtoreum, Coſtus, of each half an ounce; oyl of Foxes one ounce; Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guentum Pomatum one ounce: Indian Balſame one drachm and half: mingle them, and make thereof a Liniment, with which anoint the place affected.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Liniment to cauſe ſtifneſs of the yard, and to provoke to luſt.</head>
                  <p>Take oyl of Lillies one ounce, oyl of Caſtoreum half an ounce; Euphor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium, Pepper, Muſtardſeed, of each one drachm; Gallia Moſchata one ſcruple: oyl of Mace one drachm; Aromati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum Roſatum, half a drachm: mingle them, and make them into a Liniment, with which anoint the lower part of the belly, the yard and the reines.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Liniment to ſtop the Inordinate flux of the Tearmes</head>
                  <p>Take oyl of Quinces, Mirtles, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtich,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170251:72"/> of each half an ounce; Lapis He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matis, red Corral, Acacia, the juyce of Ciſtus of each two drachms; Unguen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Album, half an ounce; Ackornes Balanſtians, of each one drachm and half; with a little Wax, make it up into a Liniment, with which anoint the belly down to the thighs and the reins, night and morning.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Liniment for the Tearms that are ſtopped.</head>
                  <p>Take of Turpentine and Aloes, of each one drachm; Coloquintida two drachms, the ſeeds of Coloquintida one drachm, the Gall of an Ox half an ounce: mingle them, and make a ſtrong Expreſſion, adding black Sope one ounce: make thereof a Liniment, with which anoint the breaſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Liniment for the affections of the Liver, from an inflammation.</head>
                  <p>Take white and red Saunders of each two drachms; oyl of Wormwood one ounce, flowers of Succory powdered three drachms; Roſes, Violets, of each
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170251:72"/> one drachm; juyce of Succory and Wormwood, of each three drachms; make thereof a Liniment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Liniment for the paines of the Earos.</head>
                  <p>Take juyce of Rue cocted in the rine of a Pomgranate, oyl of bitter Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds three drachms; oyl of Dill, Caſtoreum, of each one drachm and half; juyce of Onyons torrefied two drachms and half; Aqua vitae two drachms: mingle them, and make thereof a Liniment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Liniment for the Wormes.</head>
                  <p>Take Mithridate, powder of Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quintida, Lignum Aloes, the Gall of an Ox, ſhavings of harts-horn, Myrrhe, of each one drachm; the beſt Aloes half a drachm, juyce of Rue and Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, of each three drachms: oyl of Wormwood one ounce: Wax as much as will ſuffice to body it into a Lini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:170251:73"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LACTES:</hi> OR, Milkes.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Almond-Milk for the Excoriation of the reines and bladder.</head>
                  <p>TAke of the flowers of Violets, Borage, of each half a handful: Liquoriſh bruiſed four drachms; the four greater Cool ſeeds of each one drach<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> winter-Cherries one drachm &amp; half, Mace one ſcruple: boyl them all in two pints of Barly water, till a third part be conſumed; then make a ſtrong Expreſſion, which with four ounces of blanched Almonds, beaten in a ſtone-Morter, make into Almond-Milke, adding at the end Red-Roſe-Water two ſpoonfulls, white Sugar four ounces: mingle them: of this drink at pleaſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:170251:73"/>
                  <head>A Milke to allay the heat of urine.</head>
                  <p>Take of the ſecond decoction of Barly three pints, the four greater Coole-ſeeds of each two drachms; white Poppy-ſeeds, and Agnus Caſtus-ſeeds of each one drachm; Almonds blanched one ounce: beat the ſeeds and the Almonds in a ſtone-Morter; then pour on the Barly water, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaſſing of them together with the Peſtil, till it acquires the Colour of Milk; which after it is ſtrained, add thereunto ſyrup of Marſh-Mallows, water-Lillies, of each two ounces; the beſt oyl of Turpentine twenty drops: mix them together: drink often of this, till the heat be allayed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Almond-Milk for the flix Dyſenteria.</head>
                  <p>Take of Smiths water, where his hot Irons are quenched, four pints, the waters of Roſes, and Mallows, of each two pints; Cinamon one ounce; Cloves half an ounce, Pomgranate-pill ſix drachms, quince-ſeed bruiſed one ounce, Maſtich half an ounce, French
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:170251:74"/> Barly half a handful, Liquoriſh bruiſed half an ounce: boyl them till a third part be conſumed, adding conſerve of quinces one ounce, conſerve of old Roſes two ounces, Sugar of Violets four ounces: boyl them a little, and with the Almonds beaten in a Morter, make a Milk, of which drink at will.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Amigaalated Milk for a Feaver.</head>
                  <p>Take of fountain-water four pints, the Leaves of Endive, Violets, and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, Bugloſs, Straw-berries, Sorrel, and Succory, of each half a handful; Maiden-hair one ounce, damask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prunes cut number twelve, Rayſons ſtoned two ounces, the rinde of the root of Fennel one one ounce, the root of Aſparagraſs half an ounce; Fennel-ſeed half an ounce; Mace, Cinamon, of each half a drachm: firſt take the roots, herbs, and fruit, and boyl them a little; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards add the Maiden-hair; after that, the Cinamon ſeeds, and berries of win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cherries, number thirty: mingle them and boyl them till half be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed: let the Coluture be Clari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and aromatized with Yellow
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170251:74"/> Saunders two dramchs; then take ſweet Almonds blanched, number thirty, Pine-Kernells half an ounce, the four greater Coole-ſeeds, of each half a drachm: let theſe be beaten well in a Morter, and with the aforeſaid deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Roſe-water, make Almond-Milk according to art, of which drink a draught every three hours, as long as neceſſity requires.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>LIXINIA:</hi> OR, Liemade of Aſhes.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Lixinium for the Dropſy.</head>
                  <p>Take of the aſhes of Broom, Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, Juniper-wood, the ſtalks of beanes, of each one pound; the aſhes of the interiour bark of Aſh, one pound and half; all which by adding water, make a Lixinium, adding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ſome white-wine, of which take four ounces, with two ounces of Sugar,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:170251:75"/> in the morning faſting, and at four of the Clock in the after-noon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Lixivium for the Dropſie and Gout.</head>
                  <p>Take of the aſhes of the Leg of a Horſe burnt one pound; bean-water ſix ounces, common ſalt half a pound: mingle them, with which waſh the parts affected.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>LOCH: OR, Eclegme or Lohoc. i. A liquid Confection thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then a ſyrup, and thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner then an Electuary.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Lohoc againſt a Cough.</head>
                  <p>TAke Lohoc de pine, Lohoc ſanum, of each three drachms; Diatragan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thum
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:170251:75"/> frigidum one ſcruple, Penni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees one ounce, Treacle one drachm; Orris, Hyſſop, Liquoriſh, the ſeeds of Mallows, Foxes Lungs, of each one drachm; ſyrup of Liquoriſh as much as will ſuffice to make it into a Lohoc or Eclegm; of which take a little often in a day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Lohoc for difficulty of breathing.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Lohoc of Fox Lungs, half an ounce: Diatraganth calid two ſcruples: Diatrion Pierion half a drachm; Orris, Liquoriſh, Enula-cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pane, Anniſeed, of each half a drachm; and with half an ounce of ſyrup of Horehound, and three drachms of ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup of Hyſſop, make it up into a Lohoc, of which take a little upon a Licoriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick ever and anon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A pectoral Lohoc for groſs and thick flegme.</head>
                  <p>Take of the juyce of Squills, Hony ſcummed, flower of Brimſtone, of each equal parts: boyl them to the Conſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of a Lohoc, of which take half a ſpoonful five or ſix times in a day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:170251:76"/>
                  <head>A Lohoc for the Cough of Children.</head>
                  <p>Take of flax-ſeed dried and beaten to powder two ounces, powder of Liccoriſh two drachms, Moſch three graines, Amber-greaſe one graine: make it with Hony into the form of a Lohoc, of which let them lick a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of it, upon the end of a Liccoriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Lohoc for the Exulceration of the Lungs.</head>
                  <p>Take Diatraganth frigid, Diacymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, of each two ſcruples; Dianiſi, Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reos, of each two drachms; Venice-Turpentine one drachm; ſyrup of Licco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, Maiden-hair, and Horehound, of each one drachm; powder of Liccoriſh half an ounce: mingle them, take half an ounce of this three times a day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Lohoc for the Aſthma, which is a diſeaſe through the ſtoppage of the Lungs, cauſing difficulty of breathing, and wheezing</head>
                  <p>Take of Rayſons ſtoned, bitter Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:170251:76"/> and ſweet blanched, of each four ounces: Turpentine one ounce, Penidees three drachms, three figs, Orris-root three drachms, juyce of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoriſh half an ounce, Saffron half a drachm, the flour of Linſeed half an ounce; and with Aſſes Milk make it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Lohoc.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Lohoc for a Pleuriſy.</head>
                  <p>Take of Enula-campane, and Colts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot of each two ounces, the Leaves of Hyſſop, Horehound, Pimpinel, Lungwort, and Maidenhair, of each one handful: Rayſons ſtoned, Figs, Dates, of each half an ounce, the ſeeds of Lin, and Mallows, of each two drach. Cinamon, Saffron, of each one ſcruple: boyl them to the juſt conſiſtency of a Lohoc, by adding thereunto Sugar Penideated half a pound, and Hony as much as will ſuffice: take of this half an ounce three times a day,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Lohoc for a Catarrhe.</head>
                  <p>Take of juyce of Liccoriſh half an ounce, the powder of Anniſeed, Enula-campane,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:170251:77"/> Licoriſh, of each one drachm the balſam of Sulphur ten graines, Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danum three graines, Storax ſtrained one ſcruple, ſyrup of Poppies, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jubees, of each one ounce and half: diſſolve the juyce of Liquoriſh, the Balſam and Laudanum in one ounce of Aqua Celeſtis: afterwards incorporate them all together, adding Clarified Hony, as much as will bring it to the Conſiſtency of a Lohoc: the doſe is the quantity of a Nutmeg going to bed, and of a ſmall Nut in the morning faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="237" facs="tcp:170251:77"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>MASTICATORIA:</hi> OR, Maſticatories; or Apophleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiſms: <hi>i. e.</hi> A Medicine chewed in the mouth, drawing humours from the Head.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Maſticatory for the Epilepſie.</head>
                  <p>TAke of Pellitory of Spain one ounce, Maſtich three drachms, White Wax as much as will ſuffice to incorporate them into little morſels, like unto the ſimilitude of a Filberd; which muſt be chewed in the mouth for half an hour, upon an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty ſtomach.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Maſticatory for the Cramp and Palſey.</head>
                  <p>Take of Green-Ginger one ounce
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:170251:78"/> and half, Muſtard-ſeed, Pellitory, of each half an ounce; of all the Peppers one drachm and half; Caſtoreum, Maſtick, of each one one drachm; ſweet Cane two drachms: mingle them, and make thereof Paſtills for Maſticatories.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Maſticatory for the pain of the head.</head>
                  <p>Take Marjoran, Sage, Betony, Mace, Nutmeg, Cloves, of each one drachm; Gallia-Moſchata half a ſcruple, Hony, Wax a little: make thereof Troches for Maſticatories.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="239" facs="tcp:170251:78"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>PESSARIA:</hi> OR, Peſſaries;</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>VVhich is a certain Medicament thruſt into the Privities of a woman, with a ſtring tyed to it, to pull it out again.</p>
               </argument>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Peſſary to bring down the Tearms gently.</head>
                  <p>TAke the powder of Mugwort, and Dittany, of each half a drachm, Myrrhe, Galbanum, Storax, Agarick, of each two ſcruples; Savine well bruiſed and beaten half a drachm; Saffron half a ſcruple, the beſt Treacle, Juniper-berries, of each one drachm, and with the juyce of Mercury make it into a Peſſary, which let it be involved in a little Sarſnet, and ſo put up.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:170251:79"/>
                  <head>A ſtronger Peſſary for the provocation of the Tearmes</head>
                  <p>Take Myrrhe, Aloes, of each one drachm; Saffron half a drachm, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniacum, the root of Gentian, Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine, of each three drachms; juyce of Wormwood, oyl of Spicknard, of each two drachms; mingle them, and make it into a Peſſary.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Peſſary to ſtay the inordinate flux of the Tearmes, or to ſtop them when they continue beyond their courſe.</head>
                  <p>Take Acacia, Gum-Arabick, Amber, Olibanum, Balanſtians, Dragons blood, of each one drachm and half; Galls, juyce of Ciſtus, of each two drachms; Mirtle-berries powdered one drachm; juyce of Knotgraſs one drachm, Frankincenſe two drachms; and with the juyce of Plantain incorporate them into a Peſſary, rolling it in Sarſnet after the form of a finger, and ſo put it up with a threed tyed to it, to pull it out again.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="139" facs="tcp:170251:79"/>
                  <head>A Peſſary to bring down the child in the womb, whether alive or dead.</head>
                  <p>Take of the root of Sowbread half an ounce, the Leaves thereof one handful, Savine two handfulls: beat them together till they come to a paſt, add thereunto the Gum Opoponax half an ounce, the juyce of Sowbread as much as will ſuffice to incorporate them into a juſt Conſiſtency: of which take as much as will make a roll as thick as ones thumb, thick at the one end, and ſmall at the other; wrap it in Sarſnet, with a threed tied to the end of it, beſmearing it with oil of Almonds, that it may paſs up into the body with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hurting the part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; and after it hath layen in twelve hours, draw it out.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Peſſary for a flux of blood.</head>
                  <p>Take Knotgraſs-root, Comfrey beaten well, of each half an ounce: Maſtich, Starch, Frankincenſe, Linſeed burnt, of each one drachm; and ſo with aſtringent juyces made into a Peſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, annexing a threed thereunto, to draw it out again.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:170251:80"/>
                  <head>A Peſſary for the ſuffocation of the Matrix.</head>
                  <p>Take Taccamahac, oyl of Mace, of each half an ounce: Gallia Moſchata, one ſcruple and half, ſpecies Aroma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticum Roſatum one drachm, Storax ſtrained two drachms; or of Spicknard, Rams ſuet, as much as will ſuffice to make it into a Peſſary.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Peſſary to cauſe Conception.</head>
                  <p>Take Storax, Spike, Caſſia, Nutmeg, the Raſpings of harts-horn, of each two drachms; Opobalſamum one drachm, white Wax three drachms; and with the marrow of a hart, make it into a Peſſary, which muſt be uſed immediately after Copulation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Peſſary for the ſwelling of the womb.</head>
                  <p>Take Frankincenſe, Galbanum, Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niacum of each one drachm; gooſe-greaſe, the Marrow of Calves Legs, the oyntment of Marſh-Mallows, of each one drachm: let the Gums be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved in Hony, and then all mixed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and ſo involved as before.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:170251:80"/>
                  <head>A Peſſary for the coming down of the womb.</head>
                  <p>Take of Caſtoreum, Maſtich, of each two drachms; Aſſafoetida one ounce: Frankincenſe, Mirtle-ſeed, of each one drachm; and with Aſtringent juyces make it up into a Peſſary.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Peſſary for the Molo, that is, a hard ſwelling, or a peece of fleſh in the womb of a woman.</head>
                  <p>Take Borage, Birthwort, Dittany, Gentian, white Hellebore, Saffron, of each half a drachm; Scammony one ſcruple, Galbanum two drachms; and with the juyce of Mint, make it into a Peſſary, to be ordered as before pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:170251:81"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>PIL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LAE:</hi> OR, Pills.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pills purging flegm, Choler and Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Leaves of Sena half a pound, Troches of Coloquintida one ounce and half, Aloes one ounce, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garick, Turbith, Rhabarb, of each two ounces: the roots of Black-Hellebore, Devills-Milk, of each one ounce: Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gridium half an ounce; let all theſe be finely beaten and ſifted: then take Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon one ounce and half: Aniſeed, Maſtich, Spike, of each a drachm; Red-Roſes one handful, ſpecies Diambrae, Diarrhodon Abatis, of each half an ounce: macerate them for fourteen days in ſtrong ſpirit of wine; make a ſtrong Expeſſion, and let the Colature be evaporated in a Bath, till it comes
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:170251:81"/> to the Conſiſtency of Hony, with which incorporate the aforeſaid powders in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a maſs for Pills.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Wonderful Pills for the Gout.</head>
                  <p>Take Lignum Sanctum three pounds, Sarſaperilla one pound, Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger two ounces, Galanga cut and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten one ounce; infuſe them in a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent quantity of Aquavitae, and let them ſtand infuſed in a hot place, well covered, for four or five days: expeſs the ſpirit out, and evaporate it to a juſt Conſiſtency. The doſe hereof is one drachm.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Other approved and moſt excellent Pills for the Gout.</head>
                  <p>Take Sarſaperilla twice waſhed, and cut very ſmall, and well bruiſed, one pound: infuſe it in ten pints of foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain water for three daies, afterwards boyl it upon a gentle fire, to ſix ounces: make thereof a ſtrong Cola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: then diſſolve of the beſt Aloes two ounces, and boyl it gently upon a fire, till its humid part is evaporated:
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:170251:82"/> then add the powder of Myrrhe and Saffron, of each two drachms; and ſo continue boyling of it, till it comes to the Conſiſtency of Hony, and make thereof a maſs for Pills; take two ſcruples of theſe made into Pills, every morning and night, and ſo to continue it for twenty days.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Purging Pills for a Catarrh.</head>
                  <p>Take Pil. Hierae cum Agarico one ſcruple and half, Pil. Cochiae, Maſtich, of each one ſcruple, ſyrup of Betony, as much as ſuffices to make it into Pills number five, of which take three after the firſt ſleep.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Approved Pills for a dry Cough.</head>
                  <p>Take of the ſeeds of white Poppy, Spickenard, Nutmeg, Olibanum, of each one drachm; Treacle half a drach. Saffron half a ſcruple: make it into Pills; keep one of them under the tongue go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſleep.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:170251:82"/>
                  <head>Others of the ſame Nature.</head>
                  <p>Take Bole-Armeniack waſhed in Roſewater one drachm and half, Starch one drachm, Gum-Arabick and Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganth, of each half a drachm; Liquo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice one drachm, Olibanum one ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Saffron a ſcruple, Sugar-Candy and Penidees, of each two drachms and half; and with Syrupe of Violets make them into Pills: one of them conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually keep under the tongue.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Other Pills curing a Catarrh.</head>
                  <p>Take of Caſtoreum, Myrrhe, Storax, Galbanum, Pepper, Nutmeg, Poppy-ſeed, of each half a ſcruple; Opium prepared in Spirit of Wine twelve grains: and with Syrupe of Horehound let them be made into Pills, to be uſed as the former.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pills purging groſs Humours.</head>
                  <p>Take of Mace, Galangal, Nutmegs, Agarick trochiſchized, Mechoacan, of each one drachm; Saffron, Cloves, Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:170251:83"/> of each half a drachm; Rhabarb half an ounce, Aloes waſhed twelve drachms, Maſtick one drachm: make thereof a maſs with Syrupe of Stoecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos: the doſe is two ſcruples made into Pills, and taken one hour before ſupper.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pills of the ſame Nature.</head>
                  <p>Take Aloes, Hierae, Diacoloquintida, Rhabarb, Troches of Agarick, of each two drachms; Scammony prepared, by wrapping it in a brown paper, and holding it over a little Brimſtone burnt upon Coals, one ſcruple and half, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick half a drachm; and with the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupe of Hops make it into a maſs for Pills: the doſe is a drachm made into Pills, faſting in the morning.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pills to provoke the Tearms.</head>
                  <p>Take ſpecies Hierae Picrae one ounce, Myrrhe, the root of Birthwort, Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron, Madder-root, Caſtoreum, of each half a drachm; extract of Mugwort one drachm and half, Steel prepared one drachm; and with the Syrupe of
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:170251:83"/> Calamint, make it into a maſs for Pills: Of which Pills, take five every other day, about that time the courſes uſed to flow.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pills to ſuppreſs the Tearms.</head>
                  <p>Take Myrrhe, Cinamon, Borax, Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia-wood, of each half a drachm: Salt of Wormwood two ſcruples, ſpecies Hierae two drachms; and with the juyce of Savine, let it be made into Pills a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thirty: of which take three every other day in the morning, uſing an hour or two exerciſe after.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pills againſt the white Fever, or the green Sickneſs.</head>
                  <p>Take Steel prepared half an ounce, Rhabarb, Aloes, of each one drachm and half; Hiera Picra two drachms, Gum-Ammoniacum, Bdellium diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in Vinegar of Squills, of each one drachm and half; Species Aromaticum Roſatum, Diambrae, Saffron, Salt of Wormwood, of each one ſcruple; Oyl of Cinamon, Cloves, of each two drops: mingle them, and make there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:170251:84"/> a maſs for Pills. Take half a drachm made into Pills, in the morning, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing the body; and ſo in the like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner before ſupper, for the ſpace of thirty dayes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pills for the ſuffocation of the Womb.</head>
                  <p>Take Treacle-Venice half an ounce, Caſtoreum two drachms, Oyl of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber one ſcruple: and with Syrupe of Stoechados make them up into a maſs for Pills.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pills to bring down the Secundines.</head>
                  <p>Take Cinamon, Savine, of each one drachm; Caſſia-lignes, Caſtoreum, of each one drachm and half; Dittany, Calamint, Birthwort, and Mugwort, of each half a drachm; Myrrhe one drachm, Saffron one ſcruple, Oyl of Amber half a ſcruple; and with the juyce of Mugwort make it into Pills: of which take one drachm every morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and night.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:170251:84"/>
                  <head>Pills to procure Maids Tearms.</head>
                  <p>Take Pil. Hierae cum Agarico one drachm and half, Pill of Opoponax three drachms: extract of Rhabarb, Centaury, and Gentian, of each one drachm; Steel prepared, <hi>(as ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by and by)</hi> four drachms, the roots of Aaron prepared, Tartar vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triolated, of each two ſcruples; the Chymical Oyl of Wormwood one ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Oyl of Cinamon and Cloves, of each ſix drops<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Syrupe of the five open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing roots, to make them up into a maſs for Pills; and make of every drachm in that maſs, ſix Pills, which gild: take two of them every morning, and ſo many alſo at four of the clock in the afternoon, drinking after them a draught of Wormwood or Steel-wine, exerciſing the body an hour after.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Method to be obſerved in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring of the afore-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Steel.</head>
                  <p>Take of the filings of ſteel as much as you pleaſe, put into a Morter; pour
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:170251:85"/> on as much Oyl of Vitriol, as will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve it: Let it lye in the Morter till it is dry: when it is dry, it will quickly be powdered, and look of a bluiſh co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour: Let it be caſt thorow a fine ſieve, and ſo preſerved.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another preſcription of Pills for the green Sickneſs.</head>
                  <p>Take Aloes two drachms, Myrrhe in powder two drachms, the roots of Gentian, round Birthwort, Dittany, and Saffron, of each one drachm; Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-roots, Mithridate, of each one drachm: and with the ſyrupe of Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, make it up into Pills, adding un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the maſs <hi>Sal Martis</hi> half a drachm, (the manner of that Salt-preparation is below preſcribed) take five of the Pills for a doſe three or four dayes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, before the new Moon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The preparation of Sal Martis, or Salt of</hi> Mars.</head>
                  <p>Take of the pureſt Oyl of Vitriol half a pound, ſpirit of Wine the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, one pound: put them together into
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:170251:85"/> a new Iron frying-pan, which muſt be covered with a large tile, and ſo ſet in a convenient place for fourteen days: the Tearm of time being ended, a Salt will appeare round about the pan; which take clean off, and put into a Glaſs, repoſing it in a place near unto the fire, that it may be preſerved for future uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another for the ſame purpoſe.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Salt of <hi>Mars</hi> two drach. powder of Gum Thraganth one ſcruple, and with the Muſilidge of Gum-Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganth make it into Pills, of every drachm twelve; of which take three every morning, drinking after them <hi>Aqua Lumbricorum,</hi> Magiſt, Sabinae, of each ſix drachms; Sugar half an ounce, excerciſing the body an hour after, uſing this method for twenty days to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Sudorifick Pills for the Venerean diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe.</head>
                  <p>Take of Sarſaperilla four ounces<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Guaiacum ſix ounces, the bark of the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:170251:86"/> ſame two ounces, China one ounce harts-horn, Ivory, of each ſix drachms; Saffron two drachms, Scutcheneel one drachm and half; Egrimony, Sage, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony, of each one handful; round Birth-wort-root one ounce and half, Carda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momes, Cloves and Galangal, of each halfa drachm: infuſe theſe in a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent quantity of ſpirit of wine for the ſpace of ten or twelve days; afterwards make a ſtrong Expreſſion, and evaporare the Colature till it comes to a perfect extract, of which extract take half a drachm; add thereunto ten grains of Antimonium, Diaphoreticum, which mix together, and take early in the morning, drinking after it a draught of the decoction before preſcribed, for the ſame diſeaſe, and ſweat two hours after; continuing in this courſe for twenty days together.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pills for the Hemorrhoids or Piles.</head>
                  <p>Take the ſeeds of white Henbane, and white Poppy, of each one drachm; Lapis Haematitis, red Corral, of each half a drachm; ſealed earth one drachm, Camphor half a ſcruple, Maſtich two
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:170251:86"/> ſcruples; and with ſyrup of Mirtles, make them into Pills, of which take half a drachm for a doſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pills for the Epilepſy.</head>
                  <p>Take Cinamon, Ginger, Maſtich, Nutmegs, Pyony-root, Hermodactyls, Turbith, of each one drachm and half; Indian Salt three drachms; Saffron, Liquoriſh, of each one ſcruple and half: Aloes one ounce, juyce of Sage and Betony, of each one ounce and half; juyce of Roſemary four ounces: let them ſtand in the Sun till they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come dry, and ſo make thereof a maſs for Pills. The doſe is half a drachm, every day before ſupper two hours.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>PIlls for the Epilepſy.</head>
                  <p>Take Aloes waſhed in Sage-water, half an ounce, Troches of Agarick three drachms; ſeeds of Piony, the roots of the ſame, Maſtich, Nutmeg, Accorus, Saffron, Salt of Betony, the powder of a dead mans Skull, of each one ſcruple; Aſſafoetida half a ſcruple, Caſtoreum twelve graines: mingle them, and with
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:170251:87"/> ſyrup of Staechados; make them into Pills: the doſe is four ſcruples.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pills for the Yellow Jaundiſe.</head>
                  <p>Take earth-worms prepared with white-wine half a drachm; Diaſpolit eight graines; with Oxymel Simplex make it into three Pills, which are to be taken in the morning, and ſo continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the ſpace of ſix, or nine days.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Purging Pills for a Gonorrhea.</head>
                  <p>Take Jalop, Diaturbith cum Rha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barbero, Mercurius dulcis, of each half a drachm; and with ſyrup of Roſes ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutive make it up into twelve Pills: taking four of them at a time, purging for three days together.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Or thus.</head>
                  <p>Take Extractum rudii half a drach. oyl of Guaiacum three drops, Mercuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us dulcis one ſcruple: make them into Pills, taking them all at a time, repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them over again for three or four days together.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:170251:87"/>
                  <head>Aſtringent Pills for a Gonorrhaea.</head>
                  <p>Take of Turpentine waſhed two ounces, boyl it gently to the Conſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of hony, to which add the powder of Nutmeg two drachms, of Colopho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one drachm, burnt Lead well waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Plantain-water half an ounce: make them up into Pills, of which take three in the morning, noone, and night.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Or thus.</head>
                  <p>Take Gum-Arabick, Thraganth, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, Mummy, Bole-Armeniack, of each as much as you pleaſe: beat them into a fine powder, and with the ſyrup of Mirtles, make thereof a Maſs for Pills: out of every drachm form four pills, taking one of them every meale, and two in the morning.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Other Pills for ſtopping a Gonorrhaea or flux of Sperm.</head>
                  <p>Take Turpentine waſhed in Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain-water one ounce: boyl it for half
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:170251:88"/> an hour in the water; afterwards mix with it theſe powders following, Bole-Armeniack, white-Poppy-ſeed, Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs, Lettice-ſeed, red-Corral, ſhav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Ivory, Agnus Caſtus-ſeed, of each half a drachm: make thereof Pills.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pills for the worms.</head>
                  <p>Take Agarick, Rhabarb, Gentian, Myrrhe, Dittany, burnt harts-horn, Mint, Coraline, Horehound, Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, of each one drachm; Saffron one ſcruple, Aloes two ſcruples: with ſyrup of Rhabarb, make thereof a Maſs for Pills: the doſe is half, continued for eight days.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pills for the Hypochondriack Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly.</head>
                  <p>Take of Cretenſian Epithimus one ounce, the beſt Aloes half an ounce, Nutmeg, Cloves, Senna, of each two drachms; Salt of Wormwood half a drachm, Gum-Amoni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>um diſſolved in Vinegar of Squills three drachms; the bark of black Hellebore ſix drachms,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:170251:88"/> Saffron one ſcruple: and with the ſyrup of Epithimus make thereof a Maſs for Pills, forming four Pills out of every drachm; adding to every drachm one ſcruple of Extractum Rudii: take three every other day faſting, or an hour before Supper.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pills for the Dropſy.</head>
                  <p>Take ſpecies Hierae ſimplicis, one drachm; the Salt of ſea-colworts, Pills of Laureol, of each one ſcruple: Elate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium four graines; mingle them, and make them into pills; divide them into two parts for two doſes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Other Pills for the ſame purpoſe.</head>
                  <p>Take Eleterium half a ſcruple, Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis Soldanellae, Ginger, Mechoachan of each one ſcruple, Galangal, Cloves, Cinamon, Saffron, of each half a ſcruple, and with the juyce of Orris make them into Pills: take three of them for a doſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="180" facs="tcp:170251:89"/>
                  <head>Pills for the windyneſs and hardneſs of the Spleen.</head>
                  <p>Take of Senna, Troches of Agarick, of each one drachm; Pills of Fuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, Annis, Maſtich<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of each one ſcruple: extract of black Hellebore, half a ſcruple, the bark of the root of Capers one drachm; Saffron half a ſcruple; and with the ſyrup of Hops, make them into Pills: the doſe is one ſcruple made into Pills before ſupper; which muſt be continued for the ſpace of thirty days.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>An excellent Pill for the head and ſtomach, called the</hi> Viati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can Pill.</head>
                  <p>Take the true Amomum, or in the want of it Aniſeed, Maſtich, Ginger, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours, Cardamoms, Cinamon, Setwel, Mace, Nutmeg, Cloves, Saffron, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bebs, Aloes-wood, Turbith, Manna, Agarick, Senna, Caſſia Lignea, the five Mirobalans, of each one ſcruple: Rha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barb one ounce, Aloes two ounces, and ſix drachms; Carduus, Scordium,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:170251:89"/> of each half a drachm; and with ſyrup of Roſes make it into a maſs; of which take the firſt day one Pill, the next day two, the next three, and on the fourth day four: they will keep the body ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luble, reſiſt poyſon, defend the ſtomach from all ill vapors, with many other vertues: it may be uſed a whole year, by taking one or two of them once in ten days. <hi>There is no Pill in the world endued with more eximious qualities then this.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pills for the mother.</head>
                  <p>Take Aſſafoetida, Caſtoreum, of each one drachm; Vine-ſeed four ſcruples: make thereof powder, and with the ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupe of Staechados, make them into Pills: of theſe take half a drachm, at night going to bed; and ſo continue for the ſpace of ten days.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pills for the pain of the head.</head>
                  <p>Take Pil. Macri two ſcruples, Roſine of Jalop four grains, Pil. Cochiae the leſſer ten grains, oyl of Juniper-berries and Nutmegs, of each three drops:
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:170251:90"/> make them into ſix Pills, to be taken in the morning.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pills for Rheum in the Eyes.</head>
                  <p>Take Extractum Rudii one ſcruple, Roſine of Jalop four graines, oyl of Guaiacum two drops: make them into Pills, and take them at once.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>POMA ODORATA:</hi> OR, Apples to ſmell to.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Apple againſt the Epilepſy.</head>
                  <p>TAke of the roots and ſeeds of Pyony, of each one drachm and half; the ſeeds of Roman Gith, macerated in Vinegar one drachm, Caſtoreum half a drachm, powder of Elkes-Clawes half a drachm, Camphor half a ſcruple. <hi>And if the diſeaſe be not</hi> per couſenſum uteri, <hi>let theſe Aromaticks
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:170251:90"/> be added:</hi> Cloves and Cinamon, of each one ſcruple; Moſch and Amber, of each grains two: and with Gum-Thraganth, diſſolved in Roſe-water, make it up into the form of an Apple, which muſt often be ſmelled to.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Apple for the plague, and the refreſhing of Languiſhing Spirits.</head>
                  <p>Take of the beſt Laudanum two drachms, Cloves, Mace, Cinamon, Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zoin, Storax, the root of Angelico, Nutmeg, ſweet-Cane, Myrrhe, Spike, Amber, Coral, Frankincenſe, of each half a drachm; Camphor half a ſcruple, Gum Juniper one ſcruple, red Roſes half a drachm, all the Sanders two ſcruples, Mace one ſcruple, oyl of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon ſix drops, oyl of Anniſeed four drops, of the beſt Bole one ſcruple, Amber half a ſcruple, Moſch four grains: and with Roſe-water and white-Wax, as much as will ſuffice to make it up into a Pomander, which muſt be often ſmelled to. <hi>This hath been often confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for a wonderful preſervative in the time of the Plague at London, 1636.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="164" facs="tcp:170251:91"/>
                  <head>A Pomander to perfume the body.</head>
                  <p>Take of Storax, Benzoin, Laudanum, of each two drachms, Rhodium-wood one drachm; damask-Roſes, half a drachm; Orris one ſcruple, duſt of ſmall-Coal one drachm and half; Musk Cod two drachms, Amber-greace and Civet, of each ten grains; oyl of Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium and Cinamon of each two drops, and with the Muſilidg of Gum-Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganth extraced in Roſe-water, as much as will ſuffice to make it into a Pomander, of what form you pleaſe; which if it be carried in the Pocket, will yeeld a moſt fragrant ſcent.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:170251:91"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>POTIONES:</hi> OR, Potions.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Purging Potion againſt the Hypochon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driack Melancholy.</head>
                  <p>TAke of ſyrup of Roſes ſolutive four ounces, Confectio Hamech three drachms, ſpecies Aroma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticum Roſatum half a drachm; mingle them, and make thereof a Potion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A purging Potion againſt Choler.</head>
                  <p>Take Rhabarb one drachm: let it be infuſed in Succory-water three ounces: ſtrain it, adding Caſſia drawn newly from the Cane, Diaman of each half an ounce; Electuary of the juyce of Roſes two drachms, oyl of Cinamon three drops: make it up into a Potion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="166" facs="tcp:170251:92"/>
                  <head>A Potion purging flegm.</head>
                  <p>Take Agarick Trochiſcized, one drachm and half; Rhabarb two dragms; Cinamon, Ginger, of each one ſcruple and half: macerate them in Hyſſop-water three ounces, for twelve hours: afterwards let it be preſſed out, and ſtrained, adding Diacarthemus, two drachms; ſyrup of Staechados half an ounce, ſpecies Aromaticum Roſatum one ſcruple: mingle them, and drink it off at a draught.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Potion purging flegm, Choler, and Melancholy.</head>
                  <p>Take of the infuſion of Senna three ounces, Diacatholicon half an ounce, Diaphaenicon two drachms, Diaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae one drachm, ſyrup of Succory one ounce, oyl of Cinamon three drops: mingle them, and make thereof a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: let it be taken in the morning, uſing the acuſtomed manner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, as ordered in all purgations.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="167" facs="tcp:170251:92"/>
                  <head>Another for the ſame end and purpoſe.</head>
                  <p>Take Rhabarb two ſcruples, Chebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan and Citron, Myrabolens, of each one ſcruple; Senna three drachms, pulp of Tamarinds one drachm and half, the Cordial flowers, of each one pugil: Squinant ten grains, Ginger ſix grains, ſweet Fennel-ſeeds half a drachm, Yellow Saunders and Citron-pill, of each half a ſcruple, Manna ſix drachms; infuſe them for twelve hours in white-wine and Succory-water, of each three ounces: ſtrain it, and add to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lature Syrupus adverſus Melancholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um of Roſes, with Agarick, of each half an ounce, Tartar Vitriolatum ten grains, ſpirit of Sulphur two or three drops: mingle it for a Potion; take it early in the morning, not drinking any poſſet-drink till it hath wrought once.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Potion againſt the ſtone and the winde of the Spleen.</head>
                  <p>Take of Senna two ounces, Cloves two ſcruples: let them be infuſed in
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:170251:93"/> half a pint of Strawberry-water, to which add the flower of Caſſia one ounce, Turpentine waſhed in Saxafrage water, and diſſolved with the Yolk of an Egg, half an ounce: Nutmeg two drachms; ſpecies Aromaticum Roſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum one drachm, ſyrup of Hops, Drop-wort, Marſh-Mallows, of each one ounce; oyl of Cinamon ſix drops, ſpirit of Sulphur one ſcruple: mingle them, and divide it into three parts, for three ſeveral Potions.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A purging Potion for the Jaundiſe.</head>
                  <p>Take Rhabarb two drachms, Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon one ſcruple, Troches of Agarick half a drachm, Ginger half a ſcruple: let them be infuſed in white-wine and Endive-water, as much as will ſuffice: let there be of the Colature three ounces: add thereunto Manna one ounce and half; mingle them, and make thereof a Potion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Or thus.</head>
                  <p>Take of Rhabarb one drachm and half, Spickenard eight grains, Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:170251:93"/> one drachm: let them be macerat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the waters of Endive and Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood for twelve hours, and to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lature or Liquor ſtrained out, add Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manna, Electuary of the juyce of Roſes, of each two drachms; Salt of Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, Diacurcumae, of each half a ſcruple, Yellow Sanders one ſcruple: mingle them for a Potion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Potion for the flix Diarrhaea.</head>
                  <p>Take of the conſerve of old Roſes, Berberies, of each half an ounce; Smal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidge prepared with ſyrup of wine two grains, Diaſcordium one drachm, Mithridate one ſcruple: diſſolve them in the waters of Plantaine, Sorrel, and Red-Roſes, of each one ounce; ſyrup of the bark of Citron-pill one ounce: mingle and make them into a Potion, to be taken in the morning faſting.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A purging Potion for the flix Dyſenteria.</head>
                  <p>Take Torrefied Rhabarb one drach. and half, Yellow Mirabolens Torre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied alſo one drachm, powder of harts-horn half a drachm, Plantain-water
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:170251:94"/> two ounces, ſyrup of dried Roſes one ounce: make it into a Potion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Potion to bring down the Secundines or after<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>birth.</head>
                  <p>Take Aloes-wood, Caſſia-wood, Myrrhe, Saffron, Cinamon, Agarick, Savine, Aſſafoetida, Amber, Caſtoreum, of each one ſcruple: Sugar one ounce and half: let them be infuſed in Aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitae; afterwards preſs out the Liquor, and drink one ounce of it for a doſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Potion to bring down the Tearms.</head>
                  <p>Take juyce of Savine one drachm; Saffron two grains, the compound wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Horſradiſh-root one ounce: Dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie it with Sugar; let it be repeated for four days together, or more, if need require.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Potion for the Mother.</head>
                  <p>Take Nutmeg bruiſed three ounces, fountain-water one pint and half: boyl them till half be conſumed; and to the Colature add white Sugar four ounces:
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:170251:94"/> boyl them a little together: of this take one ounce every morning, and at four of the Clock in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, drinking after it poſſet-drink, in which let there be boyled tops of Thyme.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Potion cauſing ſleep.</head>
                  <p>Take of the ſyrup of Poppies, Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codium, of each half an ounce: Lettice-water two ounces, Diamargarit frig. two ſcruples; mingle them, and drink it off going to bed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Potion for the Dropſy.</head>
                  <p>Take of the juyce of Orris three drachms; Elaterium ſix grains: mingle them; drink it off faſting.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another Potion for the Dropſy.</head>
                  <p>Take of Lignum Guaiacum one pound, Egrimonie one handful, Aſarabacca half a handful, Maiden-hair, Dodder, Dwarf-Elder, of each one handful and half; the five opening roots, of each half an ounce: Madder-roots, the roots of
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:170251:95"/> Orris and Elder, of each one ounce, Liquoriſh, ſea-colworts, of each three ounces; the ſeeds of Fennel, Annis, Parſly, Smallidge, Alkanet, of each one drachm; Cinamon three drachms, of the Cordial flowers, of each one pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil: the ſeeds of Meadow-Saffron one ounce and half. <hi>But if it be a Dropſy with a ſwelling of the Spleen,</hi> then add the roots of Capers, Elder, Tamarisk, and the inward bark of Aſh, of each half an ounce: boyl them in ten pints of foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain-water, and four pints of white-wine, till full four pints be conſumed: add to the Colature ſyrup of Egrimony half a pound; mingle them. The doſe is four ounces, three times a day, at morning, before dinner and ſupper.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Potion to cauſe ſweat.</head>
                  <p>Take of the beſt Treacle, one drach. Gum of Guaiacum one drachm &amp; half, Salt of Wormwood one ſcruple, Bezoar ſtone three grains, Carduus-water two ounces and half, ſpecies Aromaticum Roſatum one ſcruple and half: mingle them for a Potion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="173" facs="tcp:170251:95"/>
                  <head>Another of the ſame Nature, to drive any thing from the heart.</head>
                  <p>Take of Treacle-water three ounces, Venice-Treacle half a drachm, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kermes two ſcruples, Gaſcoin-powder one ſcruple, ſyrup of Gilliflowers one ounce: mingle them, drink it off at a draught, afterwards cover the body warm, that it may ſweat.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A cordial Potion.</head>
                  <p>Take of Damask-Roſe-water half an ounce, Citron-water two ounces, Mint-water ſix drachms, Aqua-Coeleſtis half an ounce, Aqua-Mariae two drachms, Magiſter of pearl ten grains, Alker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes two ſcruples; Syrupus Cardiacus, and ſyrup of Cinamon, of each half an ounce; mingle them for a Potion, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding into two parts for two doſes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Potion of Mechoachan, purging ſaltiſh, watriſh, and ſcorbuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal humors.</head>
                  <p>Take of Mechoachan four ounces,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:170251:96"/> Hermodacts, Guaiacum, of each three ounces: Ginger two drachms; Sarſape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilla, Liquoriſh, of each two-ounces; Nutmeg three drachms, Bindweed one ounce and half: prepare them ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as their nature requires, and put them in a bag, with one ounce of Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, including in the bag a flint-ſtone, to cauſe it to ſink to the bottome; which bag put into a little Rundlet contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing three Gallons of beer new and freſh; which after it hath ſtood five days, draw out a bowl full to drink morning and night.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Potion clarifying the blood, allaying the heat of the Liver, and purging away all ſeroſe humors.</head>
                  <p>Take Senna three ounces, Monks Rhabarb ſix ounces, Madder-roots, and Dock-roots, of each two ounces; Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word, and Drop-wort, of each one ounce and half; Sarſaperilla three ounces, Guaiacum ſix drachms, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoriſh one ounce, the Leaves of Liver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, Ceterach, Mugwort, Egrimony, Scabious; of each one hand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ul and half: Arch-Angel-flowers one handful, the
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:170251:96"/> ſeeds of Annis and Fennel, of each one ounce: include them all in a bag, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſtone therein; which bag hang in a Runlet containing three Gallons of new beer, and after five or ſix dayes drink a large draught thereof twice a day, in the morning, and at four of the Clok in the afternoon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An excellent Ponado, broth, or water-gruel for a Cough.</head>
                  <p>Take of the roots of Avens, Scabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, flower de luce, Aſarabacca, Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pody, Lovage, Columbine, Tormentil, long-Birthwort, Strawberry, Sorrel, Madder, of each one ounce: ſlice them thin, that are to be ſliced; and then take Staechados, red-Sage, Endive, Ceterach, wood-Sorrel, Maiden-haire, of each one handful; Engliſh Liquoriſh one ounce and half: boyl all theſe in two Gallons of Conduit-water till three quarts be conſumed; let it ſettle, and pour off the clear, and with it make Ponado, or water-gruel, as you would do with common water: and every meſs you eat, let it be ſweeten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Sugar-Candy on the day-time;
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:170251:97"/> and if you eat any of it at night, add theſe ſyrups thereunto.</p>
                  <p>Take ſyrup of Mirtles, Horehound, Hyſſop, Betony compound, Scabious compound, Corral, and ſpirit of Mint, of each one ounce: mingle them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and eat thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Purging prunes.</head>
                  <p>Take Senna two ounces, Anniſeed half an ounce, harts-horn half an ounce, Rhabarb two drachms; boyl them in a pint and half of water: diſſolve in the Colature three ounces of Manna; in that Liquor ſtew one pound and half of prunes, adding four ounces of Roſe-water: of thoſe prunes eat four of five every morning with three or four ſpoonfuls of the ſyrup.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="177" facs="tcp:170251:97"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LERES:</hi> OR, Powders,</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Powder for the pangs of a woman after Travel.</head>
                  <p>TAke of the greater Comfrey dry one drachm; Peach-Ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nells, Nutmegs, of each two drachms; Amber one drachm, Amber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce one ſcruple: make it into a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: the doſe is a drachm in a draught of white-wine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Or thus.</head>
                  <p>Take the ſtones of Dates and Peaches, of each one drachm and half; Nutmegs four ſcruples, Pulvis Diamarg. Calid. Annis condited, of each one drachm and half; Cinamon two ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, Saffron half a ſcruple, Sugar to the
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:170251:98"/> weight of them all; make of theſe a fine powder: take two drachms with white-wine, twice or thrice in a day, if the pains be vehement.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Powder to bring down the Tearms.</head>
                  <p>Take of choiſe Cinamon half an ounce, the roots of Birthwort, Valeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Hypoſelini, of each two drachms; Troches of Myrrhe one drachm, Saffron one ſcruple, ſpecies Diambrae two ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, Sugar to the weight of them all; make thereof a Powder: the doſe is one drachm taken in the decoction of Cicers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Powder ſtaying the courſes.</head>
                  <p>Take of the ſeeds of white-Poppies, the ſeed of white-Henbane, ſhavings of Ivory, harts-horn, Red Roſes, ſealed earth, Pomgranate-pill, of each half a drachm; Lapis Hematitis, Corral, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtich, of each one ſcruple: the doſe is half a drachm, taken in broth morning and night, which is very effectual.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="179" facs="tcp:170251:98"/>
                  <head>A Powder for a Coagulated blood, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by a fall or a bruiſe.</head>
                  <p>Take of the roots of Madder, and Rhabarb, Sperma Caeti, Mummy, Crabs-Eyes, Amber, of each one drachm; mingle them, and make thereof a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: the doſe is a drachm in Scabious-water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Powder for the preſervation of ſight.</head>
                  <p>Take Betony, Rue, Saxafrage, Salen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine, Penniroyal, Anniſeed, Eye-bright, of each half a Pugil: Cardamoms, Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Fennel, Origanum, Galangal, of each one drachm; Vervine two dragms: mingle them, and make thereof a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which muſt often be taken in broth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Powder againſt the ſtone.</head>
                  <p>Take Powder of Venice-Turpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine three drachms, winter-Cherries, Broom-ſeed, Saxafrage, Parſly, Smal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, the roots of Drop-wort, Galan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, Reſt-harrow, Agarick, of each one
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:170251:99"/> drachm; the doſe is two ſcruples, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in white-wine faſting.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Powder for the Gonorrhaea.</head>
                  <p>Take Olibanum, Corral, Troches of Camphor, Lapis Hematitis, Agnus-Caſtus-ſeed, of each one drachm; Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs two drachms, cocted Turpentine powdered three drachms, Pearle one ſcruple: mingle them, and make there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a Powder: the doſe is one drachm with the white of an Egg in a cup of red-wine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A ſneezing Powder.</head>
                  <p>Take Pellitory, Betony, Marjoran, of each one drachm, Caſtoreum, Mace, Cloves, of each half a drachm: white-Hellebore one ſcruple, Moſch two graines, Tobacco half a ſcruple: mingle them, and make thereof a Powder, which muſt be ſnuffed up at the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrills.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="181" facs="tcp:170251:99"/>
                  <head>A Powder for the coming down of the womb.</head>
                  <p>Take Akorns, Cypreſs-Nuts, Bole-Armeniack, Dragons-blood, Maſtich Balanſtians, Acacia, Frankincenſe, of each half a drachm; and when it is powdered, ſprinkle it upon the womb.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Powder for obſtructions.</head>
                  <p>Take the roots of China, flower de luce, and Sarſaperilla, Agarick, of each one drachm; Anniſeed, Fennel, and Smallidg-ſeed, of each one drachm; the filings of Steel one drachm and half; the Salt of Wormwood, Spicknard, of each one ſcruple<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sugar two ounces: mingle them, and make thereof a Powder: the doſe is one drachm and half, in white-wine, walking an hour after.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Powder to expell worms.</head>
                  <p>Take the roots of Rhabarb, Aſara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacca, and Ditany, of each one drachm; Coraline, Myrrhe, Citron-Pil, Ivory, harts-horn burnt, Purſlaine-ſeed, red,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:170251:100"/> Corral prepared, Agarick, of each half a drachm; Saffron one ſcruple: mingle them, and make thereof a Powder: the doſe is one drachm in Purſlain-water and white-wine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Powder for a Cancer in the mouth.</head>
                  <p>Take of dryed Frogs, Crabs-Eyes, and Crabs-Claws, of each one drachm; burnt harts-horn half a drachm; mingle them, and with a quill blow the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der upon the ulcer.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>SACC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LI:</hi> OR, Bags.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Sacculus to corroborate the head.</head>
                  <p>TAke of the flowers of Chamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile, Marjoran, Sage, Staechados, Betony, Roſes, of each half an ounce: Cloves, Nutmegs, of each one
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:170251:100"/> drach, ſweet Cane one drachm and half; mingle them, and let them be powder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and put into a Sacculus that is cut in the form of a Cap, the powder being quilted in it, and ſo the Cap worn up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the head.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Sacculus for the ſtomach.</head>
                  <p>Take of Nutmegs, Cloves, Cinamon, Mint, Wormwood, Red-Roſes, Galan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, ſweet Cane, of each two drachms; Maſtich, Spicknard, Storax, Caſſia-wood, Aloes-wood, of each one drachm; Moſch three grains; Gallia Moſchata one ſcruple: mingle them, and make thereof a powder for a Sacculus; which muſt be quilted, and applyed to the Region of the ſtomach, and ſo worne.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Sacculus cooling the Liver.</head>
                  <p>Take of the flowers of Buglos, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, Violets, Roſes, both the Corrals, all the Sanders, of each one drachm; water-Lillies two ſcruples, Spodium one ſcruple, Camphor half a ſcruple: mingle them, and make thereof a Sac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="184" facs="tcp:170251:101"/>
                  <head>A Sacculus for the pain in the head, Cephalalgia.</head>
                  <p>Take of the flowers of Violets, Roſes, water-Lillies, of each one Pugil; the ſeeds of Lettice, Purſlain, Henbane, white-Poppies, Lapis Hematitis, red-Corral, of each one drachm; all the Sanders, of each half a ſcruple: after they are powdered, let them be inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in a Sacculus, and applyed to the front.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>FF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MIGIA:</hi> OR, Suffumigations.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Suffumigation for an Aſthma and ulcerated Lungs.</head>
                  <p>TAke of the Leaves of Hore-hound, Coltsfoot, Hyſſop, Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den-hair, Scabious, Red-Roſes,
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:170251:101"/> of each two drachms Turpentine two drachms, Olibanum, Maſtich, Benzoin, of each one drachm, with Gum-Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganth, diſſolved in cabious water: make them into Troches, which muſt be thrown upon burning Coales, morning and night, and the fume re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the mouth and the bed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Fumigation for a Catarrh.</head>
                  <p>Take of Gum Juniper, Gum of Ivy, Red-Roſes, Stora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Benzoin, of each two drachms; the Powder of the roots of Orris, the Leaves of Horehound, of each one drachm; Maſtich, Frankincenſe, of each half a drachm; Nutmeg, Spick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard, of each one ſcruple; Saffron half a ſcruple: make thereof a groſs powder, and with a little Turpentine reduced into Troches, let the fume be received as before.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Fumigation for Hyſterical fits.</head>
                  <p>Take Galbanum, Caſtoreum, Peuce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dani, of each three drachms; Pepper one ſcruple, Opobalſamum half a ſcruple, Sulphur four grains: infuſe the Galba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:170251:102"/> in the beſt Vinegar, and let the reſt be beaten and commixed with the Galbanum; part of which lay upon a Chafing-diſh of Coals, and let the fume aſcend up at the Noſtrills and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Or thus.</head>
                  <p>Take Galliae &amp; Aliptae Moſchatae, Cinamon, Cloves, Mace, Laudanum, Storax, of each one drachm; Bayes, Marjoran, Calamus Aromaticus, Caſſia-wood, of each two drachms: let them be powdered, and with Liquid Storax made into Troches, which lay upon a Chafing-diſh of Coals, and ſet it ſo that the fume may aſcend up at the Privities.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Fumigation for the coming down of the womb.</head>
                  <p>Take of the juyce of Cyſtus, Acacia, Balanſtians, Cypreſs-Nuts, Mirtle-berries, of each a drachm and half; Frankincenſe, Olibanum, Maſtich, Dragons blood, of each one drachm: mingle them, and make thereof a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which throw upon live Coals,
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:170251:102"/> which place between your Legs, that the fume may aſcend into the womb, having a blanket wrapt cloſe about you, that no air may expire.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Fumigation to provoke the Termes.</head>
                  <p>Take of Peniroyal, Mugwort, Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mint, Marjoran, the Leaves of Bays in powder, of each one drachm and half, Caſſia-wood, Coſtus, Amomum, Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Cloves, Savine, Myrrhe, Galba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, Bay-berries, Indian Leaves, Orris-root, of each one drachm: make thereof a groſs powder, which caſt upon Coals, placed as before.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="186" facs="tcp:170251:103"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PPOSITORIA:</hi> OR, Suppoſitories.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>A Suppoſitory for ſuch as deſire to go to ſtool, but can do nothing; called by the Doctors</hi> Teneſmus.</head>
                  <p>TAke Frankincenſe, Gum-Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick, Yellow-Wax, Opium, Saffron, of each one drachm; mingle them, make them into a Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory, which put up at the fundament, anointing the end of it with Butter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Suppoſitory for the Cholick paſſions.</head>
                  <p>Take of the ſeeds of Annis, Fennel, Cummin, and Caraway, of each two ſcruples: Benedictum Laxativum, half a drachm; Coloquintida one ſcruple, Cambugia half a drachm, common Salt a drachm; and with concreted Hony
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:170251:103"/> one ounce, make a Suppoſitory, the length of ones finger.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A ſtrong and ſharp Suppoſitory.</head>
                  <p>Take Hony boyled to a juſt Conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency one ounce, Euphorbium, Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quintida, of each ſix grains; black Helle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore, Scammony, of each one ſcruple.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A common Suppoſitory.</head>
                  <p>Take Hony boyled and concreted one drachm; ſpecies Hierae one drach. Sal. Gem, Agarick, of each half a drachm: mingle them, and make there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a Suppoſitory.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="190" facs="tcp:170251:104"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SYR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PI:</hi> OR, Syrups.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A ſolutive Syrup againſt Melancholy.</head>
                  <p>TAke of the flowers of Borage and Bugloſs, Roſemary, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momile, and Germander, of each half an ounce: black Hellebore, Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, Polypody, Epithimum, of each ſix drachms; the roots of Borage, Bugloſs, and Maiden-hair, of each three dragms; Fumatory, Egrimony, of each one Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil: boyl them in water, till a third part be conſumed; add the juyce of Pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, Fumatory, of each ſix ounces: and with a good quantity of Sugar, boyl it till comes to the Conſiſtency of a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="191" facs="tcp:170251:104"/>
                  <head>A Syrup for a Hectick Feaver.</head>
                  <p>Take four ſnails prepared in white-wine, the flowers of Violets and Roſes, French Barley, Maidenhair, of each one handful and half; the flowers of Borage and Bugloſs, of each two Pugils; of the four greater Coole ſeeds, Liquoriſh, of each half an ounce: three Figs, Rayſons ſtoned ſix dragms; Quince-ſeeds, Sorrel-ſeeds, of each half an ounce: ſweet Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, Gum-Traganth, of each three drachms; Lettice and Purſlaine, of each half an ounce, burnt Ivory two dragms; white-Poppy-ſeeds two drachms; boyl them till a third part be conſumed, and to the Colature let four pound of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar be added, to boyl it up into a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Syrup purging the Spleen.</head>
                  <p>Take of the ſeeds of Smallidg, Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broom, Cardamoms<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of each half an ounce: the roots of Dwarf Elder, black Hellebore, Aſarabacca, Acorus, Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Bryony, Orris, and Capers-root, of each half an ounce: the Cordial flowers
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:170251:105"/> of each one pugil; Fumatory, Spleen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, the flowers of Sage and Roſema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, of each one handful; Senna Epithi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Polypody, of each one ounce and half: Wormwood, Tamaris, of each half a handful; Rayſons cleanſed two ounces; the ſeeds of Annis and Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, of each three drachms; Gentian, Gum Lacc. ſweet Cane, of each half an ounce: boyl them in Chalibeate-water, till the third part be conſumed; and the Colature boyl up with Sugar into a Syrup.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Hydroptical Syrup.</head>
                  <p>Take of the roots of Dwarf-Elder, Madder, Aſarabacca, of each one ounce; Orris one ounce and half, the roots of Fennel and Parſly, of each half an ounce; Dodder, Egrimony, Endive, Betony, Ceterach, Wormwood, of each one handful; Liquoriſh half an ounce, Rayſons ſtoned two ounces, the ſeeds of Meadow-Saffron bruiſed one drach. Senna two ounces and half, Polypody of the Oak four ounces, white Agarick three drachms, Turbith two drachms, the ſeeds of Melon, Carret, and Fennel,
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:170251:105"/> of each one drachm; the flowers of Broom half a handful: Ginger, Mecho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acan, Cinamon, of each two drachms; boyl them in water to twelve pints: to the Colature add our droptical Lixivium ſix ounces, Vinegar of Squills two ounc. Sugar as much as will ſuffice to boyl it up into a Syrup, according to art.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Sudorifick Syrup.</head>
                  <p>Take of Lignum Sanctum one pound, the bark of the ſame half a pound: let them be infuſed in Rheniſh-wine and water of each ſix pints, the flowers of Chamomile and Staechados, of each one handful; Liquoriſh one ounce: boyl them, and towards the end of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, add the ſeeds of Annis and Fennel, of each two drachms; Setwel, and Angelico-roots of each half an ounce, the flowers of Borage and Bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſs, of each one Pugil and half: Saffron one drachm; ſtrain it, and with a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient quantity of Sugar, boyl it up into a Syrup, adding Salt of Wormwood two drachms.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="194" facs="tcp:170251:106"/>
                  <head>A purging Syrup for the French Pox.</head>
                  <p>Take Lignum Guaiacum one pound, the bark of the ſame three ounces, Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaperilla two ounces, Hermodacts one ounce, Turbith, Mechoachan, of each half an ounce; ſweet Cane, Thyme, of each two drachms; white-wine, foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain-water, of each ſix pints: let the woods be powdered, and infuſed for the ſpace of twelve hours, upon a gentle fire, afterwards boyl it for two hours together, adding Agarick half an ounce, Maiden-hair, Staechados, of each half a Pugil: boyl them againe, and at laſt add Epithimus one ounce, the flowers of Borage, Bugloſs, and Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary, of each one Pugil; Senna one ounce and half: boyl them again gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and then ſtrain it, and let the Cola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſettle, and the limpid part boyl up with a ſufficient quantity of Sugar, till it comes to a juſt Conſiſtency.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Syrup provoking the Tearmes.</head>
                  <p>Take Fumatory, Hyſſop, Mugwort, Calamint, Marjoran, Peniroyal, Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander,
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:170251:106"/> Hops, Thyme, Mother-wort, Maiden-hair, Balme, of each one hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; Savine two ounces, the five open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing roots, of each half an ounce: Aco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, Anniſeed, Fennel-ſeed, Origanum, Cinamon, Caſſia-wood, the four grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Cool ſeeds, of each two drachms; ſweet Cane one ounce, the Cordial flowers, of each one Pugil: Madder-root one ounce and half the roots of Valerian, and Birthwort, of each half an ounce; Juniper-berries two ounces, Saffron half a drachm: let theſe be boyled in a ſufficient quantity of water; let the Colature be boyled with Hony to the juſt Conſiſtency of a Syrup.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Syrup for the ſtone.</head>
                  <p>Take of white-wine, fountain-water, of each two pints, the waters of Saxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage, and Pellitory, of each a pint: the roots of Fennel, Parſly, Saxafrage, Reſt-Harrow, of each half an ounce: the four greater Coole-ſeeds, of each two drachms; the ſeeds of Annis, ſweet-Fennel, Parſly, Saxafrage, and Smallidge, of each three drachms; the ſeeds of Cummin prepared half an ounce: Grom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel-ſeeds
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:170251:107"/> one ounce, Coriander pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared two drachms; the roots of Bind-weed one ounce, winter-Cherries two ounces, Rayſons ſtoned three ounces, Liquoriſh one ounce and half: mingle them, and boyl them till half the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor be conſumed: add to the Colature Caſſia newly extracted four ounces; and ſo with Sugar boyl it up into a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Syrup purging the Reines.</head>
                  <p>Take of the roots of Dropwort, Reſt-Harrow in powders, of each two ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, the ſeeds of Saxafrage &amp; Grumwel, winter-Cherrys, Mallows, of each one drachm; the four greater Coole-ſeeds, Aniſeed, of each half a drachm; Straw-berry-water, as much as will ſuffice to infuſe them in a Bath, adding the flour of Caſſia four ounces: afterwards ſtrain it, and with Sugar boyl it gently into a Syrup.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Syrup for the Scurvy.</head>
                  <p>Take of the juyces of Fumatory, Hops and Scurvygrſs, of each one pint; juyce
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:170251:107"/> of Egrimony and water-Creſſes of each half a pound: let them be clarifyed, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all the Sanders, of each one drachm, which with Sugar boyl up into a Syrup.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Syrup of Lemons.</head>
                  <p>Take a Lemon, and cut it in the middle, ſtuff in neatly ten Leaves of Gold; bind up the Lemon againe: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of letting out the juyce; and let the Lemon hang in the air, for three days: then preſs out the juyce, and with Sugar boyl it into a Syrup.</p>
                  <q>And this is a very good Cordial upon alloccaſions, having admirable ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues in it.</q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Syrup for a cold.</head>
                  <p>Take half a pint of Anniſeed-water, and four ounces of Damask-Roſe-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, eight ounces of white Sugar-Candy: put the water and Sugar-Candy into a Baſon, and ſet it over a Chafingdiſh of Coals; and when it boyleth, burn it as you do wine; ſtirring it till it will burn no longer: then take it off the fire, and
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:170251:108"/> put in your Roſe-water, and ſtir it till it be cold: of this take a ſpoonful at a time, as often as you pleaſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>TABELLAE:</hi> OR, Tablets.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Cordial Tablets.</head>
                  <p>TAke of ſpecies Diambrae, Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſch dulcis, Diarrhodon Abatis, both the Corrals, Laetitiae Galeni, of each one ſcruple: Aromacicum Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um, Pearl prepared, of each half a ſcruple; Moſch eight grains, Sugar two ounces, Balm-water as much as will ſuffice to make it into Tablets, of which take one at a time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Other Cordial Tablets.</head>
                  <p>Take of Loafe-Sugar half a pound: add to it Roſe-water 2 ounces, diſſolve
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:170251:108"/> it upon the fire, and coct it to a juſt Conſiſtency: then add Alkermes half an ounce, Pearle one ſcruple, Amber-greaſe ſix grains: caſt them upon a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and cut them Checquer-wiſe; eat one of them at a time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Tablets for the Epilepſy.</head>
                  <p>Take Dianthos, Diambrae, Diamarg. of each two ſcruples, the roots and ſeeds of Pyony, of each half a drachm; Aromaticum Roſatum one ſcruple and half, conſerve of Sage, our Treacle, of each one drchm; Caſtoreum half a drachm, Sugar five ounces: and with Betony-water form them into Tablets.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Tablets for the Dropſy.</head>
                  <p>Take the ſpecies of the 3 Saunders, Dialaccae, Diacurcumae magnae, of each one drachm; our Treacle one drachm and half; the ſeeds of Annis, Carret, Dwarf-Elder, and Fennel, of each half a drachm; Sugar ſix ounces: and with the water of Dwarf-Elder, make them into Tablets.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="200" facs="tcp:170251:109"/>
                  <head>Tablets Corroborating the Ventricle and Matrix</head>
                  <p>Take of ſweet Cane, Galangal, the ſpecies of the three Peppers, Diacyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momi, of each one drachm; Cloves, Mace, Spodium, all the Saunders, Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia-Moſchata, Coral, of each half a drach. Pearle one drach. Saffron one ſcruple, Amber half a ſcruple, dryed Mint one drachm, Sugar twelve ounces: and with the water of Mint, make them into Tablets.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Tablets againſt abortion.</head>
                  <p>Take of the powder of Red-Roſes, Spodium, Pearle, both the Corals, the bone in the heart of a hart, of each half a drachm; Harts horn burnt half a drachm; Rhabarb Torrefied four ſcruples, Diamargar. two ſcruples, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar of Roſemary five ounces, Roſe-water as much as will ſuffice to form them into Tablets according to art.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="201" facs="tcp:170251:109"/>
                  <head>Tablets againſt a Gonorrhaea.</head>
                  <p>Take Agnus-Caſtus-ſeeds, the ſeeds of Rue, Annis, Nettle, Mint, Lettice, Citron-pill, of each half a drachm; red-Corral, Troches of Amber, Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, Lignum-Aloes, of each two ſcruples and a half: powder of Turpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine one drachm, Sugar half a pound: form them into Tablets according to art.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Tablets cooling the Liver.</head>
                  <p>Take the ſpecies of the three Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders one drachm; red Coral prepared, Melon-ſeed, Lettice and Endive, of each one ſcruple and half; Troches of Ivory burnt two ſcruples, Diarrhodon Abatis without the hot ſpecies one drachm, ſpecies Diamarg. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rig. half a drachm; without Borage-water form them into Tablets.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="206" facs="tcp:170251:110"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ENTA:</hi> OR, Unguents.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Unguent againſt the disfigurement of the Meaſles.</head>
                  <p>TAke of the flour of Lupines, Solomons ſeal, of each half an ounce; the Cerus of Lithargie, Sarcocolla, of each one drachm; Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon-ſeed, Roſe-water, of each two drachms; oyntment of Orenge-flowers, one drachm and half; Oyl of ſweet Almonds one ounce: mingle them, and make them into an Unguent, with Hogs-ſuet, with which anoint the face where the marks are.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Oyntment to take away the prints of the ſmall Pox.</head>
                  <p>Take of ſweet Almonds two ounces,
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:170251:110"/> Dear-ſuet, Oyl of Eggs, Sperma-Caeti, of each half an ounce; Roſe-water two ounces: incorporate them together, anoint the face therewith often.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An ointment for the Scabs.</head>
                  <p>Take Quickſilver killed in the juyce of Lemons and faſting Spittle two ounces, the powder of Enula campane, Lithargie, of each one ounce: Ung. Pſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricon Alex. one ounce and half: Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine, Oyl of Bays, Ceruſs waſhed in Fumatory-water, of each ſix drachms; Oyntment of Cerus two ounces: Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>incenſe, Maſtich, of each two drachms; juyce of Fumatory half an ounce: pure Wax, Roſine of the Pine-tree, of each three drachms: mingle them, and by boyling, make them into an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguent to cool the Liver.</head>
                  <p>Take of the juyce of Succory, and Roſes, of each half an ounce: juyce of Lettice two drachms; Oyl Violets and Roſes, of each half an ounce; Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Saunders one ounce, red-Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel one drachm; the ſeeds of Sorrel,
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:170251:111"/> Endive and Purſlaine, of each half a drachm: Lambs-ſuet and Wax, of each one ounce; all the Saunders of each half a drachm: boyl them till the juyce be con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>umed; add Diarrhodon Abatis without its hot ſpecies two drachms: make it into an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An oyntment againſt the worms.</head>
                  <p>Take of the juyce of Mugwort, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, of each half an ounce, the root of round Birthwort, Dittany, of each one drachm; Oyl of Orris, Bays, of each one ounce: Gooſe-greaſe one ounce and half, Saffron two drachms: Wax as much as will ſuffice: boyl it till the juyces be conſumed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="205" facs="tcp:170251:111"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>VOMITORIA:</hi> OR, Vomiting Medicaments.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Syr. of Tobacco to cauſe vomiting.</head>
                  <p>TAke of Tobacco one ounce, white-wine-Vinegar three ounces: infuſe them for thirty hours, in a cold place: ſtrain it, and with a ſufficient quantity of Sugar coct it to a Syrup: the doſe is one ounce or ſix drachms.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Crocus Metallorum pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered half an ounce, white-wine-Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar eight ounces: infuſe them in a Bath twelve hours; ſtrain it, add white Sugar four ounces, coct it to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtency of a Liquid Oxymel. The doſe is half an ounce or ſix drachms.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="202" facs="tcp:170251:112"/>
                  <head>Another Vomit.</head>
                  <p>Take Crocus Metallorum eight grains: infuſe it in white-wine two ounces; to the Colature add Syrup of Violets one ounce: mingle them into a Vomiting Potion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Or thus.</head>
                  <p>Take Hydromel two ounces, Aſara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacca powdered one drachm: make it into a Hauſtus.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another Vomit.</head>
                  <p>Take Gillae Theophraſti, or his Salt of white-Vitriol, half a drachm; diſſolve it in any Liquor, and it will provoke gently to Vomit.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Or thus.</head>
                  <p>Take Gum. Cambugiae one ſcruple: Cremor Tartar half a ſcruple, Oxyacant one drachm; Oyl of Anniſeed three drops: mingle them, and take it in the morning, keeping within doores.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="203" facs="tcp:170251:112"/>
                  <head>A Vomiting water of Tobacco.</head>
                  <p>Take of the beſt Rheniſh-wine three pints, the Leaves of green Tobacco three handfuls; let them be diſtilled according to art, and the Liquor keep in a Glaſs well covered: the doſe is one ounce; and the Remedy is moſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Vomiting Electuary of Hellebore.</head>
                  <p>Take of white-Hellebore, dry and bruiſed, half a pound; common water ſix pints: make thereof an infuſion for three days; afterwards boyl it till half be evaporated: make an Expreſſion, to which add Hony one pound and half, and coct it to the Conſiſtency of Hony: the doſe is from an ounce and half to two ounces, taken in the decoction of Aniſeed.</p>
                  <q>But great care is to be had in the uſe of Hellebore; for according to Hippocrates judgment, it is very dangerous, and oftentimes cauſes Convulſions.</q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="208" facs="tcp:170251:113"/>
                  <head>A Vomiting Potion.</head>
                  <p>Take of the infuſion of Crocus Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallorum one ounce: Oxymel of Squills half an ounce, Mithridate one ſcruple, Carduus-water four ounces: mix them together for a Potion.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Auxilium multis ſuccus &amp; herbafuit.</q>
               <bibl>Ovid.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
